<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian purposes and resolutions.</title>
            <author>D. T. (Daniel Tuvill), d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 149 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24393.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S95608</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">71305203</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 71305203</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183926</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08180)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183926)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2211:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian purposes and resolutions.</title>
                  <author>D. T. (Daniel Tuvill), d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 238 [i.e. 264] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuell Macham, and are to be sold at the Bul-head in Paules Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Tuvill by STC (2nd ed.) and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Title within border of printer's ornaments; initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁶ B-M¹².</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, torn pages, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University of Glasgow. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183926:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183926:1"/>
            <p>CHRISTIAN PVRPOSES AND RESOLVTIONS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 7.18.25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>To will is preſent with me; but I finde no meanes to performe that which is good; ſo that in my mind I ſerue the Law of God, but in my fleſh the law of Sinne.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Samuell Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Bul-head in Paules Church-yard. 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:183926:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183926:2"/>
            <head>To the right <hi>Worſhipfull</hi> SIR HENRY MOVNTAGV, <hi>Knight, Recorder of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and one of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties learned Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any of the good and bad affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the minde, are eaſily diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, onely Loue with her Neighbour-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertues, Dutie and Gratitude are no Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites. The Ancients faigned the three Graces to be naked, that their beauties or deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb facs="tcp:183926:3"/> might not deceiue Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and painted their <hi>Gemini Amores,</hi> Children alſo desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of apparrell: ſhewing vs, that true deſire is ſimple, open, and vehement. I ſpeake partly out of ſpeculation, but more by experience. The many fauors by which I ſtand obliged vnto you, are growne to ſo great a ſum, that I being bankrupt in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit, do in the vehemency of my dutious good will, ſincerely profeſſe the debt, and wanting other meanes of ſatisfaction, I tender this poore pittance my acknowledgment. <hi>Qui gratè beneficium accipit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Ben.</note> 
               <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam eſus penſionem ſoluit,</hi> ſaieth the woorthieſt of the <hi>Stoikes:</hi> Other paiment your generous mind cannot expect, nor my meaneſſe offer. I ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:183926:3"/> entreat pardon, if I ſeem ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ambitious, thus publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to profeſſe my thankefull Paſſions; but the generall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation which attends your merit, in the frequent imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your profeſsion, and iudiciall executions of your place, is known to all: Hence I am confident, that ſo faire a minde cannot want <hi>Candor</hi> &amp; Humanity, without which Goodneſſe (if it can be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them) is rather awfull the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amiable. I might to confirme my ſelfe (if I did doubt) tell to my ſelfe thoſe many your more priuate and domesticall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertues, which attract the loue and affection of your friendes and followers; but of theſe I will rather meditate, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſcourſe, knowing that you
<pb facs="tcp:183926:4"/> affect no other Theater for your worth, then your own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. My chiefest intent in publiſhing theſe Papers, is the good of others; And it may be, that theſe imperfect Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions and Meditations in the practiſe whereof my owne ſoule hath profited, may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileable to ſome. For wee ſee, that an Empirike hath now &amp; then, that hap in curing a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, which a learned Artist wanteth. But howſoeuer my weakneſſe may depriue mee of this fruit, yet ſhall theſe leaues remaine as a proofe and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony (which are my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond aymes) of your kindneſſe, and my thankefulneſſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:183926:4"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>E. Lucan: ad Piſonem.</bibl>
               <lg>
                  <l>— <hi>Accipe nostri</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Certus, &amp; hoc verè complectere pignus amoris,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quòd ſi digna tuo minus eſt haec nomine charta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At voluiſſe ſat eſt, animum non verbula jacto.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah! take in gree, truſting my kind intent,</l>
                  <l>This, (ah! ſmal this) my true loues monument;</l>
                  <l>And if this worthleſſe page be now too baſe,</l>
                  <l>That in theſe blots your name ſhould haue a place.</l>
                  <l>Yet well to will is all, and that's in me,</l>
                  <l>In that my vaunts, not in theſe papers be.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <lg>
               <l>Accept my heart; and here at ydle houres</l>
               <l>Read me, as you haue made me, wholy YOVRS.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:183926:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE cauſe of making theſe Purpoſes and Reſolutions co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, is not common: It is my knowne weakeneſſe, not conceit of their worthines. There are ſome, that think the vertues of learned and famous men to bee admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not imitable; but if workes of Grace appeare in a meaner perſon, by not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing to ouertake him, they begin to follow him. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> before his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect conuerſion, thought a
<pb facs="tcp:183926:5"/> chriſtian life too difficult for his then wauering minde, but when he perceiued ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vnlearned women, and ruder <hi>Artiſans</hi> to be great proficients in the Schoole of Chriſt, he then in holy emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation emboldned himſelfe, and his conſcience preached, <hi>Tu non poteris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confeſſ. lib. <hi>8</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quod iſti, &amp; iſtae?</hi> Canst not thou doe as much as theſe, and theſe? and in another place; <hi>Surgunt indocti &amp; Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum rapiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>An quia praeceſſerunt pudet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui, &amp; non pudet nec ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſequi?</hi> The ignorant riſe vp, and lay violent handes vpon the Kingdome
<pb facs="tcp:183926:6"/> of Heauen. Becauſe they went before, art thou aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to follow; or rather, art thou not aſhamed not to doe ſo much as followe? The firme reſolution of them, which were moſt likely to faint, added ſuch vigour, and conſtancy to this Saints endeuours, that though hee came the lateſt, yet he went the furtheſt in Chriſtianity. I knowe, I feele my owne frailty and imperfection, and yet truſting to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and mercy of my God, I haue ſet my reſt to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe theſe publiſhed purpoſes and Reſolutions. It is my hope that my boldneſſe will
<pb facs="tcp:183926:6"/> encourage others not to thinke the way hard, or the iourney troubleſome, being vndertake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſo mipotent a trauailer. I haue not in the preſcribing of my intended courſe affected curioſitie, but proceeded in a naturall and free ſtraine, as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which then came into my minde, did ſeeme to lead me. I expect not, I deſire not popular applauſe. If I finde in peruſing my worke the infirmities of holy Iob, that I handle a good matter ill, I reioyce in it, not becauſe I handle it ill, but becauſe the matter is good: and I had rather with
<pb facs="tcp:183926:7"/> that godly Father betray my ignorance, in imperfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcourſing vppon a good ſubiect, then ſhew wit and learning with his three no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble friends, in maintaining any argument of a differing Mold.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:183926:7"/>
            <head>CHRISTIAN <hi>Purpoſes and</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is eaſier for a man to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde vnto himſelf thoſe thinges which are ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to be don, then to do thoſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23.</note> which were ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:183926:8"/> to bee propounded. There is a Lawe in our members, ſaieth that mortified Apoſtle <hi>Paule,</hi> rebelling againſt the law of our minds, and lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs Captiues to the Law of ſinne; ſo that we can no ſooner incline to what is good, but euill is ready to ſeduce vs. The Lambe of God, Chriſt Ieſus, is no ſooner come into the worlde, but <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> like a bloody Wolfe doth eagerly purſue him. A thought of <hi>Piety</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee conceiued, but Sathan ſeeketh to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it He would cruſh
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:183926:8"/> it in the womb for feare it ſhoulde eſcape him in the Cradle. I will labour therfore by feruent prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and godly Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for a daily ſupplye from the Spirit, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſe to continue my ſuite, till a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination become a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect will.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>THe ſoule of man, the more it deſireth the fruition of any temporal &amp; changeable good, the more it differeth from
<pb facs="tcp:183926:9"/>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:183926:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:183926:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:183926:11"/> that incorporeall, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and vnchaungeable God, in whoſe ſeruice is perfect freedom, and the knowledge of whome is life euerlaſting. I will no longer therefore doate vppon the ſpecious out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of this deceitfull world: I wil diuorce my ſelfe wholy from the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities thereof, &amp; eſpouſe my beſt affections to none but him: I will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſimilitude with him in his operations, &amp; that I may the ſafelier flye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, I wil fly vnto him, borne thither on the wings of Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:183926:11"/> and Action; of Faith and Charity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>IT is not enough for vs to forbeare that whych is bad, we muſt giue our ſelues withall to do that which is good. <hi>Ceaſe to do euill, learne to doe well;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaih 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeeke iudgement; releeue him that is oppreſſed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge the fatherleſſe, and defend the Widdowe; then will I reaſon with you,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and were your ſinnes redder then the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>million, I will make them
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:183926:12"/> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter then ſnowe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>were they redder then Scarlet, I will make them whiter then wooll.</hi> Not euery one that cryeth Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.2.</note> Lord, but hee that walketh vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, &amp; worketh righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, it is hee that ſhall dwell in the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of the higheſt, it is he that ſhall reſt in his holy Mountaine, and be neuer moued. It ſufficeth not that we haue Lamps in our hands; for vnleſſe they flame out in loue towards God, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity towards our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, we ſhall neuer bee ſuffered to followe the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:183926:12"/> Bride-groome into his nuptiall Chamber.<note place="margin">Mat. 12.13.</note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are inuited to the feaſt, but he that preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to come, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing on his wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhal be bounde in Chaines, and caſt into vtter darkeneſſe, where there is nothing but wai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling &amp; gnaſhing of teeth. I will not onely there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhun the blindneſſe of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but I will ſeeke for the light that ſhineth in the land of <hi>Goſhen:</hi> and howſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe the lord to beſtow vpon me but a meane Talent, I will husband it ſo well,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:183926:13"/> that when he ſhal cal me to giue vp an account of my Stewardſhip, I may return it back with good encreaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>IIII.</head>
               <p>THe Soul dieth when it is forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God; the bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when it is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of the Soule; the whole Man, when the Soule which is forſaken of God, dooth likewiſe forſake the Body; for then neyther dooth the ſoule liue by GOD, nor the bodye by the ſoule.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:183926:13"/> For how can that bodie properly be ſaide to liue, which hath a Soule an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to it, not to giue it life, but to make it ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of paine. Whileſt I ſoiourne therefore heer on earth, I wil order my actions in ſuch manner, that as my bodye recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth being fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſoule, ſo may my ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her Creator. I will labour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to liue vnto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, that I may neuer die but vnto ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>V.</head>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:183926:14"/>
               <p>WHatſoeuer a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoweth, that ſhal he alſo reape. If hee ſow to the fleſh, he ſhal reape corruption; if to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, life euerlaſting. <hi>Let vs therefore not be wearie,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Gal. 6, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>of doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well, for in due ſeaſon ſhall we reape, if we do not faint.</hi> He that ſtriueth for a Maiſtry, vnles he ſtriue as he ought to doe,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.5.</note> ſhall neuer bee crowned. <hi>I am the true Vine,</hi> ſayeth our Sauiour, <hi>and my Father is the husband man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 15.4.</note> 
                  <hi>euerie braunch that beareth not fruite in me, hee taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: &amp; euerie one that bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:183926:14"/> he purgeth that it may bring forth more.</hi> But as the braunch cannot bear of it ſelfe, except it abide in the Vine; no more can we, except we abide in him. Whoſoeuer put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his hande to the Plough,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.13</note> and looketh backe, ſhall neuer enter into the ioies of heauen; but he that indureth to the end, he ſhalbe ſaued. Chriſt Ieſus would not deſcend from the croſſe, when he was willed vnto it by the Iewes, bee cauſe he woulde not leaue the worke of our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnperfect: and when
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:183926:15"/> the Prince of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <hi>Peter,</hi> vpon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation which hee made them, of thoſe particular troubles hee was to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vpon his arriual at <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> out of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his loue, deſired him to haue ſome pittie and compaſſion on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and not to goe; <hi>Get thee behind me Sathan,</hi> ſaid he,<note place="margin">Mar. 8.33.</note> 
                  <hi>thou art a ſcandall and a ſtumbling blocke to my proceedings; Thou vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeſt not the things that are of GOD, but onely the thinges that are of Men;</hi> ſuch was his perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in accompliſhing the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:183926:15"/> fulneſſe of our ſaluation. In my iourney therefore to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num 11.5.</note> how tedious, and howe weariſome ſoeuer it may ſeeme, I will not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Fleſh-Pots of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt:</hi> I will be mindefull alwaies of the Wife of <hi>Lot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 19.17.</note> and in my paſſage vnto <hi>Zoar,</hi> I will followe the directions of my bleſſed guid, and neither linger on the plains, nor looke once backe vppon the ruines of ſinneful <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> for feare I diſpleaſe the Author of my ſafety, and that my puniſhment be made the monument
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:183926:16"/> of my diſobedience; I will forget that which is behind, and endeauor my ſelfe to that which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;<note place="margin">Philip. 3.13</note> I will follow hard towardes the marke, for the price of that high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and neuer ceaſe to runne, till I haue finiſhed my courſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>GOds wrath, though it come ſoftly, yet if commeth ſurely, and in the end, what it wanted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:183926:16"/> in ſwiftneſſe, it bringeth with it in ſeuereneſſe. I will not therefore abuſe his gentleneſſe, nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume too much vpon his patience. He is beautiful as <hi>Tirzah,</hi> comely as <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant 6.3.</note> but terrible with al, as an Army with ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Hee is like thoſe <hi>Cherubins</hi> in <hi>Ezechiell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 41.19.</note> he hath the face of a Lyon, as well as of a man. Hee will ſend his tempeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad with fury, and like a Whirle-winde ſhall it light vppon the head of the vngodly:<note place="margin">Ier. 30.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Aram</hi> ſhall come before, the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims</hi> ſhall come behind,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:183926:17"/> and deuoure the rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Iſraell</hi> with open mouth. I will ſeeke vnto him therfore in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and at noone-day; yea in the euening will I call vppon him: I will make my praier vnto him in an acceptable time,<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.13.</note> &amp; he ſhall heare mee in the multitude of his mercy, and in the trueth of his ſaluation: The Lord ſhal teach me his way, and I will walke in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements; hee ſhall knit my heart vnto him, and I wil feare his name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:183926:17"/>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>GOD hath not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny neede of the bloud of Bullocks, or of the fat of Beaſts, or of any other corruptible and earthly thing, no not ſo much as of the verie righteouſneſſe of man. If wee worſhip him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rules preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vs by his word, in Spirite and in Truth, the profite heereof redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not to him, but to our ſelues. For who ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:183926:18"/> ſenſeleſſe as to thinke he benefites the Sun, when he beholdes his beames, or that he pleaſureth the Spring, when hee drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the water. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer therefore my deedes are, I will deſire but acceptance, and that which followeth after, I will attribute to his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, not to my ovvne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>THe omnipotency of the word, appeareth in nothing more, then
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:183926:18"/> in that it maketh all thoſe omnipotent that doe hope in it. <hi>Ioſhua</hi> commandeth the Sunne to ſtand,<note place="margin">2. King. 20.10.</note> and it obeyeth him: King <hi>Ezechias</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that the ſhaddowe of it may retire, &amp; <hi>Iſaiah</hi> graunteth it. Yea Chriſt himſelfe aſſureth vs, that were our Faith but as a graine of Muſtard-ſeede,<note place="margin">Mat. 17, 20.</note> we ſhould no ſooner ſay vnto a Mountaine, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue;</hi> but it ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be remooued, and nothing at all ſhould be impoſſible vnto vs. I wil not therefore with the Scribes and Phariſes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:183926:19"/> a ſigne for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of my increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;<note place="margin">Mat. 12.38.</note> but without putting my fingers with <hi>Didymus</hi> into the printes of his Nailes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.25.</note> or my handes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his wounded ſide; I will beleeue without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions or demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the ſacred myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Incarnation, Paſſion, Reſurrection, &amp; Aſcention of my moſt holy and bleſſed Sauior; humbly beſeeching him,<note place="margin">Luke 17.5.</note> with his Apoſtles, that hee would vouchſafe to ſtrengthen and encreaſe my Fayth,<note place="margin">Col. 1.23.</note> that I may continue grounded and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:183926:19"/> eſtabliſhed therein, and not bee mooued away from the hope of that glorious Goſpell, which hath beene preached by his choſen Miniſters to euery creature that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>MANS intention without Gods aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, auaileth nothing. <hi>Peter</hi> was but a while forſaken,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.27</note> and howſoeuer he did abound with loue and zeale, yet was hee notwithſtanding ſuppla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Enemy: his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:183926:20"/> faith was ouerwhelmed with feare; hee forſooke him for whom he ſwore to dye. Gods aſſiſtaunce without mans intention profits as litle; For what action, circumſtaunce, or exhortation could be thought requiſite for the reclayming of <hi>Iudas,</hi> which Chriſt omitted; but al was to no purpoſe hee was a Deuill, and ſo he dyed. And heereupon the Lord himſelfe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth in the 23. of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Hieruſalem, Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 23.37.</note> 
                  <hi>which killeſt the Prophets, and ſtonest them that are ſent vnto thee;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:183926:20"/> how often would I haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered thy Children toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as the Hen gathereth her Chickens vnder her Winges, and ye would not?</hi> GOD pointes vs to the ſprings of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly grace, but vnleſſe we ſtoope to the Well, we cannot be refreſhed with the water. We lie wallowing heere in the mire of earthly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, and in vaine ſhall he aſſay to raiſe vs if wee be not willing to riſe; If hee lende vs his hand, wee muſt giue him our heart, or rot and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trify in our own infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. In al humility there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:183926:21"/> &amp; ſingleneſſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, I will deſire the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of my ſaluation that he would vouchſafe to ſecond my holy Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, and ſo quicken mee according to his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindnes, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe him to call vnto me, I may be inſtantly ready to runne vnto him, applying my ſelfe without delay, to keepe his Statutes and commaundements.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 18 22.</note>OBedience is more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the Lord
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:183926:21"/> then ſacrifice, &amp; to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken then the fat of Rams. <hi>To what purpoſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>bringeſt thou incenſe vnto me from Sheba,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 6.20.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſweet Calamus from a far Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey?</hi> He deſireth not the bloud of Bullocks, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he delighted with the multitude of burnt offeringes;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.14.</note> ſo hee may haue vs, he careth not for what is ours. When I ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to my Creator therefore, I will not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vp the Calues of my lippes, without the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of my heart; I wil not giue part to him, &amp; keep the choiſeſt for my
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:183926:22"/> ſelfe. All the Fat is the Lordes,<note place="margin">Leuit. 3.16.</note> &amp; he that eateth it ſhall bee cut off from his people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>THE Couetous man is like a Chriſtmaſſe Boxe; whatſoeuer is put into it, nothing can bee taken out of it, till it bee broken: Hee ſoaketh vp the waters like a Spung, and till death doe come and ſqueeze him with his Iron Graſpe, he will not yeeld one drop: his hand is ſound and nimble to receiue, but when hee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:183926:22"/> ſhold vſe it to relieue the wantes of his diſtreſſed Brother, it lyeth withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his boſome, &amp; can by no meanes poſſible be ſtretched out. Hee wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth out himſelfe in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring for that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee hath no vſe. Hee knoweth no God of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth, but his Gold: his reſtleſſe purchaſe of it is his reſt, and with religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous admiration doe his thoughtes adore it: hee thinkes it Sacriledge to diminiſh the leaſt heape, but the time will come, when he ſhall goe as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out of the world, as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:183926:23"/> euer he came into it, and then thoſe Aungels in which hee gloried heere, ſhall bee ſo many Deuils to torment him there. Whereas he that dealeth his Bread vnto the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.34</note> and bringeth the poore vnto his Houſe; his light ſhal break forth as the morning, and his health ſhall growe with ſpeede: his righteouſnes ſhall go before him, and the glory of the Lorde ſhall embrace him.<note place="margin">Eſay 58.7.</note> He ſhall bee like a Garden that is watered, and like a Spring, that can neuer faile; his very
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:183926:23"/> bones ſhal fatten, and his Soule bee ſatisfied in the midſt of drought. I will continually therfore caſt my Bread vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and according to that portion which the Lord hath lent mee, bee alwaies ready to releeue the needy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>I Will not mortify my ſelfe in part, nor in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting with thoſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <hi>Amalekites</hi> that ſeek the ruine of my Soule, will I make <hi>Saul</hi> my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent; but according to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:183926:24"/> the mandate of my God, <hi>Demoliar vniuerſa,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.3</note> I will bring downe all; I will not ſpare Man, woman, nor Childe. For here are thoſe three ſins to which we are all ſubiect: Firſt, the ſin of frailty, behold the Woman. Secondly, the ſinne of Malice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Man: Laſt of al the ſinne of Ignorance, behold the Childe. Nay I will labour as much as in mee lyeth, to deſtroy the very heardes, with euery other thing, &amp; not leaue ſo much as the leaſt circumſtance, that may either aggrauate or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:183926:24"/> extenuate my offences; So ſhall I fight the good fight, and in the ende re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that ineſtimable price which is laid vp for mee in the Kingdome of glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>GOD is not an <hi>Italie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated</hi> Courtier; nor doth hee euer entertaine vs with Lippe-courteſie. When he inuiteth vs,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.</note> we muſt in no wiſe ſay him nay; Hee will pull vs to him with the Cordes of a Man, and drawe vs on
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:183926:25"/> eeuen with the bands of loue; And when he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that this is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, hee will ſende his Chaſticementes and his Corrections for vs, who like faithful Meſſengers, will not be ſatisfied with any vain excuſes,<note place="margin">Luke 14.23</note> but wil compell vs by violence to come vnto him. It is not the purchaſe of a Farme; the buying of an Oxe, nor the marrying of a wife, that will ſerue our turne. The Mayſter of the Feaſt hath ſent for vs, and we muſt goe. His Dinner is prepared; hee hath killed his Fatlinges,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.4.</note>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:183926:25"/> and all thinges nowe are in a readineſſe. If hee ſee that his Table bee not thorowly furniſhed with Gueſts, he will inſtantlie grow exceeding wroth, and woe be to vs, if once hee ſend his Warriours forth.<note place="margin">Eſay 41.2.</note> For then ſhall we bee giuen as Duſt vnto their Swordes, and as ſcattered Stubble vnto their Bowes. I will not therefore ſlightly regard his inuitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. He ſhal no ſooner call but I wil free my ſelfe from all encum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances and come:<note place="margin">Luk. 14 15</note> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I know is he that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Bread in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom<note place="margin">Reuel. 19, 9</note>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:183926:26"/> of God, and ſitteth at Supper with the holy Lambe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XIIII.</head>
               <p>IN this World there is a threefold roade. The one is, that of Chriſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ill to good, from ſinne to Grace, which beginneth at the Valley of <hi>Hinnon,</hi> &amp; reaches to the Mount of <hi>Oliues,</hi> and thorough this haue al the holy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches, Prophets, and Apoſtles iournyed from time to time to theyr e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall happineſſe. The other is that of ADAM, from good to ill, from
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:183926:26"/> life to death, and goeth downe from <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Ierico:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 10.30</note> It is a way that is exceeding dangerous, and beſet on euery ſide with Theeues and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, that wil rob vs of thoſe vertues wherwith wee are arayed, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wounded vs wil go their way, leauing vs there alone to languiſh in our miſery. The third and laſt, is that of ſathan, which is round and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. He compaſſeth the earth, and like a roaring Lyon he walketh about,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.7.</note> ſeeking whom hee may deuour.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note> To go right for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:183926:27"/> is no pace for him; he muſt continually bee turning, and the reaſon hereof is this; he would not reſt himſelfe when time did ſerue in the lord his God, who as he is to all Creatures, the firſt efficient of their beeing, ſo is he the laſt final cauſe of their working, &amp; as it were the breathing ſtop and period of their ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. But his motion hath no center, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt bee alwayes wheeling. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongeſt them all then I wil ſelect the firſt. It is ſtraight and ready, and will quickly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:183926:27"/> bring a man to his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted harbour:<note place="margin">Luke 10.4.</note> Being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred once into it, whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I meete, I will let him paſſe according to the precept of my bleſſed Sauiour,<note place="margin">1 King 4.29.</note> and not ſalute him; If hee ſalute mee, I will not aunſwere him. He treads a path direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary to mine, and I will not ſeeme by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementing to affect his company.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>THE wicked man is a great <hi>Linguiſt.</hi> Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:183926:28"/> deſire in him hath his peculiar ſpeech, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry paſſion his proper dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. His boſome is the very <hi>Babell</hi> of al confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Wiſedom may not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding cry till ſhe bee hoarſe, there is not one that vnderſtands her accent. The toongs they ſpeake withal are forked, but not fiery,<note place="margin">Actes 2.3.</note> and cannot therfore ſerue for vnion, but diuiſion. They are ſuch as will ſooner bring a punniſhment vpon the ſpeaker, then cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. I will leaue them therefore to him that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:183926:28"/> them; and not ſuffer a Thought within my breaſt,<note place="margin">Eſay 19.18</note> that ſpeaketh any language but that of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p>THe Lord is liberall,<note place="margin">Iames 1.5.</note> and reproacheth no man. There is not the leaſt, &amp; meaneſt of thoſe benefites, which euery moment wee receiue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, but is farre more then wee could deſerue, farre more then we durſt deſire. Hee neuer values that which he giues, yet
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:183926:29"/> giues hee alwayes that which is pure and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. He will not flatter our hopes with verball Complements,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.24.</note> nor tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture them with vaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laies. <hi>Aske, and you ſhall receiue</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt) <hi>that your ioy may bee fulfilled.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 12.19</note> The world doth otherwiſe: Faire promiſes, but ſlowe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance: &amp; in the end, Inſteade of bread it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vs a ſtone; inſtead of fiſh it feedes vs with a Serpent: we looked for a ſubſtance, and beholde a ſhadow. <hi>My Soule</hi> (ſaid the rich man in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:183926:29"/> 
                  <hi>thou haſt much goods laid vppe for many yeares; liue at eaſe, eate, drinke, &amp; take thy paſtime;</hi> when loe that very night it was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him; and the goods, which he had ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered were he knew not whoſe.<note place="margin">Iere. 4.23.</note> The earth is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate and void (ſaith the GOD of <hi>Iſraell</hi>) by the mouth of his holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: it can afforde no pleaſure, which is not counterfaite and Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; the beſt things in it are ſophiſticated. The Wine therof is mingled with water;<note place="margin">Eſay 1.22.</note> and the Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of it is turned into
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:183926:30"/> droſſe. I will take no thought therfore for my life,<note place="margin">Pſal. 55, 22.</note> what I ſhall eate; nor for my body, what I ſhall put on; but caſt my burden on the Lord,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6, 19</note> and hee ſhall nouriſh mee; I will labour to bee rich in good workes, laying vp in ſtore for my ſelf a ſure foundation againſt the time to come, that I may obtaine a bleſſed and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life: ſtill cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſomewhat at the handes of God, that hee may ſtill haue occaſion to giue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:183926:30"/>
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>BEtter it is (ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) to bee of hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mind with the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Prou. 19, 9.</note> then to deuide the ſpoyles with the proud. Wrath &amp; confuſion ſhal follow theſe; but grace and glory ſhall be giuen vnto thoſe. <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſhall be preferred before <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes;</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſhais</hi> little one before the reſt of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: <hi>Adonijah</hi> may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his elderſhippe,<note place="margin">Gen: 48, 20 1. Sam. 16, 11. 1 King 1.30.</note> but <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhall enioy the Kingdome. It is <hi>Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> that maketh vs accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God and Man,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:183926:31"/> whereas the contrarie maketh vs hated and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred of both. While <hi>Saul</hi> was little in his own ſight, GOD made him head ouer the tribes of <hi>Iſraell.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.16.17. Let vs but looke vppon the life of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and wee ſhall ſee that hee drew more peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto him in his Ecli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſed and obſcure eſtate, then hee did in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent of his glory. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly three were preſent at his tranſfiguration in the Mount;<note place="margin">Mat. 17.12.</note> but lying in a Manger ther came kings to worſhippe him,<note place="margin">Luke 9.28.</note> and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:183926:31"/> Sheepheardes to adore him.<note place="margin">Math. 2.2.</note> And when he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelfe ſo farre, as to become obedient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.32.</note> yea to the death of the Croſſe, then was his exaltation; for then he drew all thinges vnto him. <hi>Learne therefore of me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for I am meek and lowly of heart.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 11, 29.</note> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed where ſhall we find a more glorious prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, then is the Patron of all glory,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.67.</note> who beeing in the forme of God, did clean annihilate himſelf, &amp; took on him the ſhape of a Seruant. The pride of Heauen became the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:183926:32"/> ſcorn of Earth: The ſon of God, the ſlaue of man. He left his fathers court, (ſuch was the loue hee bare vs) to come and cure the Vlcerous Infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of our infected Soules.<note place="margin">Phil. 2.5.</note> Hee did abaſe himſelfe that hee might honor vs; and was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of his owne dignity to purchaſe ours. I will labour therfore that the ſame mind which was in him towardes mee, may likewiſe bee in mee to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others. I will not boaſt my ſelfe againſt the Publican, nor as one that had taſted of the Leauen<note place="margin">Luk. 18.11</note>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:183926:32"/> of the Phariſes, thinke better of my ſelfe then I am, or worſe of others then they are, but deſire God that he would deck mee inwardly with low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of Spirite,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5, 5, 6</note> that I may be exalted of him in due time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <p>OVR Sauiour is not of that outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, that worldly Princes are: his traine is ſmall, himſelf not charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; He doth not looke for ſumptuous prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:183926:33"/> The Holy-Ghoſt is his Harbinger, who (ſo the heart bee cleane) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes no Ceremonies.<note place="margin">Luke 11.40.41.</note> 
                  <hi>Martha</hi> buſied her ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his ſeruice, but Chriſt reproued her: he tolde her ſhee was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with many thinges, but one alone was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; and that her Siſter <hi>Mary,</hi> who ſate at his feete, and heard his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, had choſen the better part, which ſhold neuer be taken from her. For indeede it is not the ſtatelineſſe of the houſe, nor the ſumptuouſneſſe of the Table, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:183926:33"/> in. He viſiteth the Sonne of <hi>Alpheus</hi> at the receite of Cuſtome;<note place="margin">Mar. 2.14.</note> he goes in with <hi>Zacheus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 19 5</note> &amp; ſits at board with Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Sinners. There is no man ſo meane, but may find meanes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent him: Hee that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and beleeueth his worde, dooth feaſt him royally. Let any Man,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.23.</note> (ſaith he) harbour in his boſome a louing affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards mee,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3, 20</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, I and my Father will come and dwel with him for euer. I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauor therfore to clenſe my Soule from all impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:183926:34"/> I will caſt out of it thoſe many vices &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, wherewith euen from my Cradle it was tapiſtred. It ſhall no longer be a Denne of Theeus and Murtherers. It ſhall no longer bee a <hi>Rendez-vous</hi> for Sin and Sathan; I will make it a Houſe of Prayer, a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle for the liuing GOD. I will adorne it with Faith and hope, but aboue al,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13, 1.</note> with Loue and Charity,<note place="margin">Mat. 21, 14.</note> without which the very voice of Angels is but as ſounding braſſe or a tinckling Cymball: and there will I preſent
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:183926:34"/> vnto him my halting Thoughtes, and blinded vnderſtanding, that hee may heale them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <p>IT were better neuer to haue knowne the way of Righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.21 Heb. 6, 4.</note> then hauing known it, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the holy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement which was giuen vnto vs. It is impoſſible, that ſuch as haue taſted of the heauenly guift, &amp; were made partakers of the Holy-Ghoſt, if once
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:183926:35"/> they fall away, ſhould be renewed by repentance: They crucify again vnto themſelues the Sonne of God, &amp; count the bloud of the Teſtament as an vnholy thing.<note place="margin">Mat. 12.43</note> The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of vncleanneſſe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired vnto his former home, and with him ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen others worſe then himſelf are come, ſo that the latter end of theſe, is more diſaſtrous far then their begining. They are returned like the Dogge to their own vomit;<note place="margin">Prou. 26.11</note> and like the Sowe that was waſhed to the wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Myre: <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:183926:35"/> is gone backe to <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 9.3.</note> and eateth thinges that are vncleane in ASHVR. They hadde the victory of ſinnefull fleſh, but they knew not how to vſe it. 'Tis ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched againe (as it were) out of their Iawes; and loe; Of Conquerours, they become Captiues. Their actions haue a fair beginning, but the ende is faulty: They reſemble <hi>Nebucadnezzars</hi> Image;<note place="margin">Dan. 2, 32.</note> their head is of fine gold, but the feete of them are Clay. They hold forth a Rod with <hi>Aaron,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it flouriſheth,<note place="margin">Num. 17, 8 Exod. 14, 3.</note> but by
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:183926:36"/> and by it falleth to the ground and becommeth a Serpent. Laſt of al, they are like him, that offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a Lambe for his Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Lorde,<note place="margin">Leuit. 3, 9.</note> but the taile of it is wanting; which God himſelfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Prieſt ſo ſtrictly and preciſely, to take euen altogether to the very Chine, and burn vpon his Altar. I wil en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour therefore to bee conſtant in my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings; and like the <hi>Bee</hi> till I haue ſucked the ſweetneſſe which I look for out of one floure, not range vnto an other: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:183926:36"/> wel aſſured, that the Apoſtls themſelues, had they not continued in Prayer, &amp; Thankſgiuing to the Lord, could neuer haue receiued the holy Comforter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <p>THE Foxes haue holes,<note place="margin">Math. 8.20</note> the Birdes of the Heauen haue neſtes; but the Sonne of man complayneth, that hee hath nothing whereon to reſt his head. Tis compaſſed about vvith
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:183926:37"/> Thornes, and few there are that dare ſuffer him to approach them. The Couetous man will not endure him: <hi>Whoſoeuer he be,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 14.33</note> 
                  <hi>that forſaketh not all hee hath, can neuer bee my Diſciple,</hi> woulde pierce him to the quicke. The proud cannot away with him:<note place="margin">Mat. 11, 29.</note> 
                  <hi>Learne of mee, for I am meek and humble,</hi> wold much diſquiet him. The carnall and voluptuous liuer will by no meanes entertain him: for ſhold hee but looke vppon the auſtereneſſe of his life, &amp; conſider with himſelfe, that,<note place="margin">Math. 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed onely are the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:183926:37"/> pure of heart,</hi> it would ſo goar his conſcience, that hee ſhoulde not poſſibly reſt. In a worde, all men in a maner vtterly forſake him Hee commeth into the Countrey of the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darenes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Marke 5, 17</note> and ere he enter their Citty, they beſeech him to depart theyr Coaſts. He repaireth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and there they ſeeke to ſtone him. Som of the meaner ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would willingly recei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him, but the Phariſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> terre them from i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bid them looke i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Rulers did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> He fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:183926:38"/>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:183926:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:183926:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:183926:40"/> in the breaſt of <hi>Pilate</hi> to ſhade him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nas 4.6.</note> that cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular &amp; ſcorching heate, wherewith his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries did purſue him: But alaſſe! It ſprung vp in one night, and periſhed in another: <hi>Priuate-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> came as a Worme, and waſted it. And now behold the burning Sun and the blaſting Winde begin to beate vppon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> head; hee brings him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and deliuers him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe! It is to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The Heire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ineyarde, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> is Fathers a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> comes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ites t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:183926:40"/> but the husbandmen are agreede to caſt him out of it, and ſlay him. So that his complaint is not without iuſt cauſe. For want of harbor, he ſeeks the deſert places, and is forced in the night to reſt his weary Limbes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in a Garden, where hee hath no Bed, but the cold Earth; no ſheet, but the moyſt Ayre; no Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopy, but the wide Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. I will runne th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore and meete him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Abra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Angels.) I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> him to wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:183926:41"/> my roofe, and when his Enemies ſhall come and aske for him, I will not part with him. I will bring forth my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, my beloued Sins, that they may glut their malice vpon them: He ſhall reſt in my boſome: I will make for him a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Chamber (as did the <hi>Shunamite</hi> for <hi>Eliſha</hi>) and ſet therin a Bed, a ſtoole, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Table, and a Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, that he may dwell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e for euer. Let his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> neuer ſo ſharpe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll bolſter it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hinke that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge hath
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:183926:41"/> tooke impreſſion there, vnleſſe I ſee it like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, all bloudy and full of woundes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <p>THE Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is exceeding po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke, &amp; much abounds with craft in his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges. He knowes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> things which were o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bruiſed, may bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> broken; He kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Wood whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> times kind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly burn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hee ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:183926:42"/> commit ſuch ſinnes as in former times they were accuſtomed vnto. Hee is withall a cunning <hi>Rhetoritian,</hi> and doth vſe much <hi>Sophiſtry.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 19.5.</note> He neuer comes to the point but by inſinuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: He vſurps vppon them by degrees, and deales with them as the father of the <hi>Leuites</hi> did with him; by little &amp; little hee procures theyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nſent vnto that, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it ſummarily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, would perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tterly reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> are twoe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> oftentimes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> captiuate
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:183926:42"/> the Soule of Man. The one is Pleaſure; which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaw that Chriſt reſiſted, hee did aſſaulte him with the other, which was <hi>Griefe,</hi> the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Engin as he thought for battry of the twaine. And lo he ſtirred al men vp againſt him; his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples hee cauſed to deny their Maiſter; the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to deride their ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine; the paſſengers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> blaſpheme their Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and in a word, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to crucify their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that hee forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out; Beh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:183926:43"/> ſee if euer there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny griefe that may bee thought to parallel this of mine.<note place="margin">Lam. 2, 12.</note> But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this hee findes him ſtill inuincible. The cruell dolours of his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments cannot make him forget to praye for his Tormentours. I will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies therefore ſtriue to fortify the weaker place; and where the Foe ſhall haue made a breach, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll erect a Bulwarke. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the perſwaſions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>baddon,</hi> of that <hi>Bad</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> euer ſo enticing. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te my Maiſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeke t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:183926:43"/> them with a <hi>Seriptum eſt.</hi> When God hath giuen mee a precept, I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to performe it. The Spirite of <hi>Vntruth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King 13.18.</note> though in the mouth of a Prophet, ſhall not be ſtrong enough to diuert mee from it. The Lorde will ſende a Lyon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the diſobedient, &amp; his Carkaſe ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the Sepulcher of his Fathers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:183926:44"/>
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <p>THere is a league of amity between God and the good; nay, there is an inward familiarity; a very neer affinity. They are his friendes; they are his followers; they are his true borne Sons. But notwithſtanding this the Lord of might, the ſtrict exactor of all vertues, is no way fonde of them; he carrieth a ſharp hand ouer them, and doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vre them to hard-meate
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:183926:44"/> euen from their Cradle. Hee loues not to make a wanton of the leaſt. Hee doth try them; hee doth traine them; and maketh them fit for his own pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. There is not any thing wherein hee more delighteth, then in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> encounter ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with aduerſity. Thrice onely were the Heauens opened: Firſt,<note place="margin">Ezech. 1, 1.</note> to <hi>Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,</hi> when at the Riuer <hi>Chebar</hi> he did addict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto diuiner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation: Secondly to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mar. 3.16.</note> when on the bankes of <hi>Iordan</hi> he was Baptized of <hi>Iohn;</hi> And
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:183926:45"/> laſt of all to <hi>Stephen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes 7, 56</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in honour of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Mayſter, he plaid his prize with Death, &amp; wraſtled with the Deuill and the damned; and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were they opened wide, that both himſelfe and his whole Court might behold the braue perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Combat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. The Earth is as his Theater, whereon hee ſtageth ſuch as are his, &amp; maketh them a ſpectacle (as the Apoſtle ſaith) for the World,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4, 9.</note> for Angels, and for Men. Sloath ſhal not conſume their Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; nor eaſe effeminate
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:183926:45"/> their mindes. Hee will make them ſweate euen vppon Holy-daies. One accident or other ſhall prouoke their valour,<note place="margin">Gen: 32, 28</note> &amp; keepe it from growing ſluggiſh thorough want of exerciſe. An Angell if all ſhoulde faile, muſt come down from aboue and wreſtle with them till the breaking of the day, to keepe them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in breath, and to preuent their Sinnewes from waxing numbe for lacke of motion: And they themſelues are well contented with it. They count affliction but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:183926:46"/> and are in pain but when they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed. They know not what it is to yeeld: when they can ſtand no longer on their feete, they will fight vppon their knees. Theyr death ſhall be the Trophy of their victory, their patience the monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that muſt adorne their graue. Though there be cries and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations throughout the Land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> yet reſt and quietneſſe is found in <hi>Goſhen.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de Ciu. Dei. <hi>1,</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> The fire may conſume the wood, but it makes bright the gold; the Flaile may bruiſe the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:183926:46"/> Huske, but it cleanſeth the Corne: <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoaſt are ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Sea, but <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> doe march with ſafety tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the middeſt of it. The wicked ſhrink vnder the burthen of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but the courage of the righteous is no more altered therewith; then is the ſaltneſſe of the Sea with the violent and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous fluxe of thoſe many waters which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually doe fall into it. Let affliction therefore come, I will meete it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently as <hi>Iob</hi> did; I will
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:183926:47"/> deſire it for the loue of Chriſt, as the Martyrs did; yea, I will reioyce in it as the Apoſtles did,<note place="margin">Actes 5.41.</note> who after they had been beaten by the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, reioycing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer rebuke for his Name,<note place="margin">Iames 2.2.</note> I will not thinke my ioy accompliſhed, but when I ſee my ſelfe hedged in on euery ſide with croſſes, hindrances, and tribulations. The thought of the price ſhal make me delighted with the paine.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5, 5.</note> I will not care
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:183926:47"/> for the loſſe of my fleſh, ſo my Spirite may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the day of the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <p>THere are ſome vices of that Nature,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6, 8.</note> they cannot bee vanquiſhed but by auoiding. <hi>Fly For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication;</hi> ſaieth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paule:</hi> Truſt not to thine own ſtrength; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not vppon thine owne ſufficiency: Her faction is exceeding ſtrong; there are thoſe in thee, and about thee,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:183926:48"/> which vnleſſe thou o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlooke them with as many eyes, as had thoſe myſticall Creatures of <hi>Ezechiell,</hi> will treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly betray thee. The Fleſh is an alluring <hi>Dali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 3, 7.</note> Not <hi>Sampſon</hi> with his ſtrength; nor <hi>Salomon</hi> with his Wiſedome are able any way to preuent her Stratagems. The ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtrong men of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant of <hi>Iſraell</hi> that were about his bed could not protect him. If ſhee get within thee, ſhee is ſure to foyle thee. When I ſee her therefore make towards me, I wil thinke
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:183926:48"/> it no diſparagement to turne my backe. There is valour euen in retreate. Our Sauiour fleeth, and <hi>Herod</hi> followeth; yet in the ende the <hi>Tetrach</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes his Captiue; and notwithſtanding the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage which hee had, muſt grace the trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall Charret of Chriſt the Conquerour. But whether I bee forced to fly from <hi>Herod,</hi> or from <hi>Aegypt;</hi> from Sinne, or from Sathan, I wil deſire the Lord I may be ſtil ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math 2.13</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and the litle Babe; the firſt is the bitterneſſe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:183926:49"/> of Repentance; the laſt is the pureneſſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; and the other an augmentation or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of Grace, with which euery where euen in the mouth of Hell: without which no where, not in the Gates of Heauen, can we reſt ſecurely. We may crye out vnto him with the fooliſh virgins, <hi>Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, open vnto vs;</hi> but if theſe bee away, his anſwere will be, <hi>I doe not know you.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:183926:49"/>
               <head>XXIIII.</head>
               <p>THere was not any thing in the world af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fal of <hi>Adam,</hi> which did not in ſome meaſure beare a part of his pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. All things did degenerate from theyr creation; and from that time became obnoxious to corruption. The Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments themſelues did waxe impure. The earth brought nothing foorth but Thornes &amp; Thiſtles: It had in it that mightie <hi>Behemoth</hi> to moleſt it;<note place="margin">Gen. 3, 18. Iob. 40, 10.</note> &amp; the Water that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:183926:50"/> 
                  <hi>Liviathan</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it. But Chriſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one of holy ones, came downe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſanctified the one by walking too and fro vpon it; &amp; the other, by cauſing himſelfe to be Baptized with it: He pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified the Ayre by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in it; and the Fire by ſending his holy Spirite in the likeneſſe of it. Man who was indeed that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer Leauen, which cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the whole lump, was to be cleanſed from his impurity, not vvith the fat of Buls and goats, nor with the Aſhes of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:183926:50"/> an Heyfer,<note place="margin">Heb. 9, 14.</note> but with the precious bloud of that immaculate and ſpotles Lambe, who thorough the eternall Spirite offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelf without blot or blemiſh to the Lord, that he might purge the Conſcience from dead workes, and make it fit to ſerue the liuing God. As the Childe of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence therefore I will no longer faſhion my ſelfe to the former luſts of an vnbrideled Affection;<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.13.</note> I will bee ſober, and relye wholly on the grace which is brought vnto me by the reuelation of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:183926:51"/> my bleſſed Sauiour. The Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his wounds ſhal be the <hi>Iordan</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I wil alwaies waſh my loathſome, leaprous, and exulcerated Soule. I will endeauour, that as hee which hath called me, is holy, ſo may I likewiſe be holy in all manner of conuerſation, that both of me, and of others hee may bee glorified in the day of the viſitation.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.12.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <p>PRofaneneſſe is the badge of baſenes, but
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:183926:51"/> a religious and vpright heart is the enſigne of true gentry. Such as are the Children of <hi>Abraham</hi> will doe the works of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 8.39.</note> They will bring foorth nothing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace their birth, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice their breeding.<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3, 10</note> Their Actions ſhal haue alwaies written in theyr fronts the liuely Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of their Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Others may boaſt of their deſcent, but they are no better then the ſpurious Iſſue of an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roike Father.<note place="margin">Gen: 16, 12.</note> They are a wilde and ſauage gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: The Bond-Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:183926:52"/> is their Mother. They haue nothing in them that is truely gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous:<note place="margin">Gen. 21, 10</note> and ſhall therefore be caſt out with <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> from beeing partners of the promiſe with the lawful Heire. The father of <hi>Canaan</hi> for his impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall be made a Slaue; and the King of <hi>Babell</hi> for his pride ſhall become a Beaſt. The Wealth and and glory of the World, with thoſe hydropicall and puffed vppe Titles, which are the foode and Fodder of Ambition. what are they elſe but i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginary and fantaſtick
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:183926:52"/> graces, of ſlender ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, of ſhort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuaunce? The feare of the Lord is the height of Honour, and hee that is vertuous is only Noble. I wil labor alwaies ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to doe righteouſly; &amp; teach my hart the way of Gods Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.<note place="margin">Actes 17.11</note> The Men of <hi>Berea</hi> were preferred by the holy Ghoſt before thoſe of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> becauſe they ſearched the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures with more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and receiued the word which was taught them with morewilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I will doe as they
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:183926:53"/> did, and obtain the ſame ſtile which they had. I will delight in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of my God, &amp; with his precepts will I ſolace my Soule.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXVI.</head>
               <p>THE Lord is a good God, ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſſe. Hee deſireth not the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe of a Sinner; (<hi>Why will ye dye,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>O Houſe of Iſraell?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eze. 33, 11</note>) But rather that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from his wicked waies and liue. Though
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:183926:53"/> in the heate of his wrath and indignation, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the fearefull ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Death againſt him; yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if he fal from his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer courſes, and ſubiect himſelfe vnto his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, hee will reuerſe his iudgements, hee will annihilate his doombe. Hee knoweth of what Moule we be made; hee remembreth that we are but Duſt;<note place="margin">Pſal. 103, 14</note> that our daies are but Graſſe; and that as the flower of the field, ſo flouriſh we. He excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth our manifold tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions vpon our weak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:183926:54"/> that hee may not puniſh them as procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from wilfulneſſe. <hi>I know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ye did it of ignoraunce.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes 2, 17</note> There is in his boſome a louing and kinde affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs. Hee pleadeth our cauſe himſelfe; and ſeeketh to remooue the guilt, that hee may ſpare the guilty. He forgetteth the place of a Iudge, to performe the part of a father. He inuiteth them that are thirſty to the Fountaines of liuing Water; and willeth ſuch ſuch as are heauy laden to come vnto him, that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:183926:54"/> he may eaſe them; And when thorough vile and obſtinate contempt of this his kindneſſe, they fall into a bottomleſſe &amp; immeaſurable Gulfe of miſerie, his hart is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with pittie and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and out of the commiſeration which he hath of the wretchednes of their eſtate, he cryeth out by the mouth of his holy Prophet; <hi>Oh! That thou hadſt hearkened to my Commandements,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 48.18 Iere. 48.31</note> 
                  <hi>then had thy proſperitie beene as the Floud, and thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as the Waues of the Sea.</hi> Hee is in all thinges
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:183926:55"/> GOD omnipotent; yet there are three thinges which lye without the compaſſe of his power: He cannot deny his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to him that ſeeketh with inward ſorrow and deiection for it, nor with draw his grace from him that is vnwilling to part with it.<note place="margin">Cadant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici, dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci interci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant.</note> 
                  <hi>Farewell Friendes ſo Foes may perriſh,</hi> is no principle in his Politiks, no precept of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding; Hee cannot puniſh the wicked, where there is danger of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the godly, hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when hee intended the ruine and ſubuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:183926:55"/> of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 19, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Haſt thee</hi> (ſaid he to <hi>Lot) from hence and ſaue thy ſelfe, for I can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing til thou be gone.</hi> And in the Goſpell, he would not ſuffer the Seruants of the houſhold to pluck vp the Tares, for feare they ſhould offende the Wheate, <hi>Mathew</hi> 13, 29. Hence-forward therfore I will forſake my wicked wayes;<note place="margin">Pſal. 123, 2.</note> I will abandon mine own imaginations, and with ſpeede returne vnto the Lorde. As the eyes of a Seruant looke vnto the handes of his Maiſter: or the eyes of a
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:183926:56"/> Maide to the handes of her Miſtris, euen ſo ſhal mine without ceaſing or interruption waite vpon my GOD, till hee doe crowne me with mercy, till he receiue mee to his glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXVIII.</head>
               <p>THe Maieſty of chriſt is wondrous great; his Empire is exceeding large. There is nothing in all this ſpacious <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe</hi> which lyeth not within the compaſſe of his iuriſdiction. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:183926:56"/> are his by birth, as he is the onely Sonne of his Father, begotten be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all Worldes; And heere are thoſe ſelected troopes of Saintes and Martyrs, thoſe trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall Conquerors, that haue giuen the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe to Sinne and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and doe now waite vppon the Throne of the Lambe, hauing their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies clothed with white aray, and their Temples crowned with wreathes of victory. The Earth is his by donation. <hi>I will giue thee the Heathen for thine inheritaunce,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſalm. 2, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>and the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:183926:57"/> endes of the World for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> poſſeſsions;</hi> and here had he planted thoſe renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Colonies</hi> of Warlike Combattants,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5, 8 Ephe. 6, 14.</note> that haue their loynes continually girded about with Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and vpon their head the Helmet of <hi>Saluation;</hi> that holde the Shielde of <hi>Faith</hi> in one hand, the Sword of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in the other, and are ready at the leaſt <hi>alarum</hi> to reſcue both their owne honour and their Maiſters from the fierce inuaſions and aſſaults of the aduerſary. The lower partes are his by Conqueſt.<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee hath
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:183926:57"/> ſpoyled the principalities, and powers; hee hath made a ſhew of them openly, and hath triumphed ouer them in the Croſſe:</hi> And heere is as it were the Gaole, which himſelfe appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; prepared for thoſe faint and crauen Spirits, that make a glorious flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the time of peace, but abandon their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and forſake his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours in the day of tryall, yeelding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues baſely before the conflict priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>Temptation.</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions to Angels are at his command. The winds are obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to his voice,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:183926:58"/> and the Waues are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at his rebuke. God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath mightily exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, and proclaimed by the ſound of his trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet: <hi>That at the Name o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ieſus euery knee ſhold bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ph l. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>both of thinges in Heauen, and thinges in Earth, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thinges vnder the Earth</hi> and <hi>That euery toong ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> confeſſe him to bee the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vnto the glory of the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Yet there are ſome that out of the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ofane<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of their minds, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hardneſſe of their he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> deny his power, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> at no hands acknowled<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him for their Superiour,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:183926:58"/> They cry out with the Iewes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.15.</note> 
                  <hi>We haue no K. but Caeſar:</hi> But theſe are reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for the black of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſhall for euer be diſabled from being fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-heirs with him in his euerlaſting Kingdom. I wil alwaies therefore do homage to him as my Lorde; I will take heede how I fall from ſo great a GOD; I wil fight as I ought to do, that I may be crowned when I haue doone: Hee that is the righteous Iudge ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mee at the latter day, and not mee onely, but likewiſe all thoſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:183926:59"/> that loue his appearing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXVIII.</head>
               <p>THere is no fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip between <hi>light</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6, 15</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 5, 4</note> and <hi>Belial.</hi> The <hi>Arke,</hi> &amp; <hi>Dagon</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lodge vnder one roofe. The Rod of <hi>Aaron</hi> will deuour thoſe of the Soothſaiers and Inchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and the Walles of <hi>Iericho</hi> fall downe,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 6, 20.</note> before the Tabernacle of the Lord. Hee that will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low GOD, and retaine him, muſt haue no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:183926:59"/> at all on wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Mammon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 104, 5</note> The <hi>Holy-one</hi> of <hi>Iſraell</hi> is exceeding great. It is he that ſet the Earth on her Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and couered it with the deepe as with a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He will not brook a partner in his Dignity, nor yet reſigne his glory to a third. Mans heart is that which he demands; and he will haue it all, or none. He that thinkes to ſhift him of with parte, may peraduenture periſh in his owne Hypocriſie,<note place="margin">Actes 5, 5.</note> as <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a</hi> did. I will not therefore put newe Wine into an<note place="margin">Math 9.16</note>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:183926:60"/> old Veſſel, nor piece out an olde Garment with new Cloath; I will caſt away all the woorkes of darkneſſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.12</note> and put on the compleat armor of light, I will worſhip the Lord my God, and him onely will I ſerue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXIX.</head>
               <p>THe Sunſhine of the wicked laſteth but a while:<note place="margin">Iob. 20.6.</note> It is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouercaſt; and the ioy of <hi>Hypocrites</hi> doth vaniſh in a moment: though his excellency mount vp to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:183926:60"/> Heauen, and his head do reach vnto the Cloudes, yet ſhall he periſh fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer like his Dung, and they which haue ſeene him ſhall ſay, <hi>Where is he?</hi> The worldly pleaſures whereon he feedes with ſuch a rauening and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable Appetite, ſhall fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t aſunder his entrails. His meate ſhall turne within his Bowels into the Gall of <hi>Aſpes;</hi> and howe ſweete ſoeuer it ſeeme in his mouth, it ſhall bee moſt vnſauorie in his Maw. Nor ſhal his State and condition bee ſo wretched in this
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:183926:61"/> World, but it ſhall bee more in the Worlde to come. Such feare and horrour ſhall hedge him in on euery ſide in that dreadful day, that he ſhal not know which way to runne, nor whether to retire.<note place="margin">Reuel. 1, 16</note> Aboue him ſhall hee ſee an angry Iudge, out of whoſe mouth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a ſharp two-edged Sword;<note place="margin">Ibid. 6, 16.</note> and well may he then entreate the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to fal downe vpon him, and the Hils to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of him that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lambe,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:183926:61"/> but it ſhall little auayle him. At his right hand hee ſhall diſcouer the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous &amp; diſtorted brood of his tranſgreſſions, which challenge him for their patron, and will by no meanes be induced to forſake him. At his left, will ſtand the Deuill his Accuſer, who then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folds his <hi>Ephemerides,</hi> &amp; leaues not the leaſt of all his ſinfull actions vnato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miz'd. Hee quotes them like a cunning <hi>Regiſter,</hi> with euery particular cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, both of time and place. Hee bringeth forth to his reproach &amp;
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:183926:62"/> diſaduantage thoſe fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and polluted Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in which he took him, and as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren to their Father, ſo ſaith he vnto the lord. <hi>Behold, this haue I found, ſee now whether it bee the Coate of any of thy Sonnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen: 37, 32</note> 
                  <hi>or no.</hi> If he turne back his eyes into himſelf, he ſhal meete there with the <hi>Worme of Conſcience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 66.24</note> that doth neuer dye; If he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect them on the <hi>World;</hi> he ſhall perceiue it to be nothing round about him but a burning flame. If hee caſt them downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes he ſhall there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcry
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:183926:62"/> to his perpetual ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and affrightment, that vnquenchable Lake of Fire and Brimſtone, which is prepared for him; The plentiful years are paſt; the yeares of dearth and ſcarſitie are come, and nowe not ſo much as one drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall euer be granted him,<note place="margin">Luke 16.24</note> to quallifie the heat of his inflamed tongue. The Moth-eaten. Robe ſhall exclaim againſt the proud, and the cankered Gold againſt the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous: The ſtone ſhall cry out of the walagainſt the Vſurer,<note place="margin">Iames 5.3.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Hab. 2.11,</note> that buildes his
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:183926:63"/> neſt vppon the ruines of the oppreſſed, and the Beame out of the Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhall anſwere it. The whole world and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is therein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſhall ſtand vppe in iudgement, and witneſſe againſt the Reprobate. Then ſhal they confeſſe, that it had beene better that they had neuer been borne, or that a Milſtone beeing tyed about theyr Necke, they had been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from out their Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and caſt into the ſea. While I haue time ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.6.</note> I wil waſh my hart from all vncleanneſſe, I
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:183926:63"/> will take my leaue of all iniquity, and bid farewel for euer to al profaneſſe and impiety.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.7.</note> I will alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether exerciſe my ſelfe to godlines, which hath annexed vnto it the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the life preſent, and of that that is to come.<note place="margin">Pſal. 71, 14.</note> The Lorde is my helper and deliuerer in the time of trouble, he is my Rocke, and my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, I will continually waite vpon him, and wil praiſe him more &amp; more. My mouth ſhall rehearſe his righteouſneſſe, and my tongue ſhall ſpeak of his ſaluation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:183926:64"/>
               <head>XXX.</head>
               <p>IT is not good for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee confident in his owne ſtrength: It is a broken ſtaffe and wil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his truſt. Hee that is in heart a Chriſtian, muſt worke out his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation with feare and trembling.<note place="margin">Mat. 26.35</note> Who before hand ſo bold in vaunts &amp; proteſtations to followe Chriſt as <hi>Peter,</hi> and yet alaſſe!<note place="margin">Iohn. 11.16</note> who at the point more timorous? Who ſo ready to dye with him
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:183926:64"/> as <hi>Thomas,</hi> yet in the end who more incredulous? Vnleſſe hee might ſee in his handes the printes of the Nailes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 20, 25.</note> he would not beleeue his reſurrection. Let him that ſtandeth, therefore looke well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his footing that he do not fall. Let him not think vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Security</hi> while hee is heere; It is not a Creature of this world. The Angels are not ſure of it in Heauen; There <hi>Lucifer</hi> did fall euen in the preſence of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. Poore <hi>Adam</hi> found by woefull experience, that it was not amongſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:183926:65"/> the Trees of <hi>Eden,</hi> for there fell hee from that eſtate of bleſſedneſſe in which hee was created; Much leſſe ought we to hope for it in this Vale of miſery,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note> where our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary like a roaring Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on walketh about, and ſeeketh whom hee may deuoure. I will alwaies therefore ſtand vpon my guard,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.41</note> I will continually keepe Centinel ouer my heart, and without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing wil I pray, that I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into Tentation. The GOD of <hi>Abraham;</hi> the Shielde of <hi>Iſaac;</hi> and the ſtrength of <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhal
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:183926:65"/> protect me. The watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſleepeth nor ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bereth, ſhall ſtil preſerue mee as the Apple of his Eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXXI.</head>
               <p>HEE that walketh in the Sunne, ſhall bee tanned; and he that med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with Pitch, ſhall bee defiled. A Man can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuerſe with ſuch as are infected, and yet reſt free from all contagion. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was but a while in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:183926:66"/> 
                  <hi>Aegypt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 34, 5</note> when he learned to ſweare by the life of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> And hence it was, that the Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> were commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Lord, to make no Couenant with the Inhabitantes of <hi>Canaan,</hi> nor to take their Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters eyther for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, or for their Sonnes, leaſt when they went a who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after their Goddes, and did ſacrifice vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they likewiſe might bee induced by them to do the like.<note place="margin">Iudg. 16, 18</note> But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſtrictneſſe of this <hi>Mandate, Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> would haue his <hi>Dali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah;</hi>
                  <pb n="211" facs="tcp:183926:66"/> and ſhee indeede did dally with him, till ſhee had deſtroied him. <hi>Dauid</hi> would entertain a league of amity with <hi>Hanun</hi> for the courteſies he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from his Father <hi>Nahaſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.4</note> but the euent of it was this: His kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was ſuſpected, his Meſſengers diſgraced. There were not women enow in <hi>Iſraell</hi> for King <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King 11.1.</note> but he muſt take vnto him the Daughter of <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> and he muſt haue with him them of <hi>Moab, Ammon, Edom, Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> &amp; <hi>Heth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Kings 11.11.</note> But the lord grewe angry with him
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:183926:67"/> for it. Hee rent his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from him, &amp; gaue it to his Seruaunt. For theſe had weaned him from God vnto Idolatry, and had enticed him to builde high places vnto <hi>Chemoſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 24, 3.</note> &amp; vnto <hi>Molech.</hi> The holy Patriarks were more obedient: <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> would none of them for <hi>Iſaac;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 27.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſaac</hi> woulde none of them for <hi>Iacob;</hi> nor <hi>Iacob</hi> for himſelfe: Hee went according to his Fathers wil to <hi>Padan-Aram,</hi> to the Houſe of <hi>Bethuel</hi> for a wife, when wicked <hi>Eſau,</hi> of purpoſe as it were to ſpite both
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:183926:67"/> God &amp; his Parents, did go to <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and tooke vnto the wiues he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, of the ſame ſtocke <hi>Mahalath,</hi> his Daughter; but for this his diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the promiſe vvas confirmed vnto his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and he himſelfe was made a Seruaunt vnto him. Though I ſoiourne therefore here on earth, my conuerſation ſhall be in Heauen, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence I looke for my Redeemer, the Lorde Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. 3.20.</note> who ſhall chaunge my vile body, and faſhion it in glory like vnto his owne, according to the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:183926:68"/> working, whereby he is able, euen to ſubdue all thinges vnto himſelfe Let the Daughters of men bee neuer ſo faire,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.2.</note> I will auoyd their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. I knowe the World had net beene drowned, if the Sonnes of GOD would haue forborne them. Our heauenly lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is exceeding iealous, If he ſee vs familiar with his Enemies, hee miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtes our hearts, and thinkes that eyther wee are already of the party, or may in time bee eaſily made ſo. The deſtructio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> the Son o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:183926:68"/> 
                  <hi>Iehoram</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> came of God, in that he went downe to ſee <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Ahab,</hi> who lay diſeaſed at <hi>Iz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cron. 22.</note> If mine eie do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cauſe me to offend, I will pluck it out; if my hand, I will cut it off, and caſt it from me.<note place="margin">Math. 18, 6.</note> Better it is that I ſhould want a member, then my whole body ſhould be caſt into Hell. There is not any one, eyther in bloud or otherwiſe, ſo neere vnto mee, but if hee fall from God, I will fal from him. Our Sauior Chriſt hath taught me, both by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:183926:69"/> and example, that I ſhold acknowledge non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for my Brother, my Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or my Mother, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch as do the will of my Father,<note place="margin">Mat. 12, 50.</note> which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXXII.</head>
               <p>MY Sonne, ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 3, 11.</note> deſpiſe not the chaſtening of the Lorde, nor faint with griefe at his rebuke. Hee correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him whom hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth beſt, euen as the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent doth the Childe in which he delighteth
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:183926:69"/> moſt. Hee will ſee how patiently hee can endure his wrath, &amp; with what conſtancy abide the ſmar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting of his rod. For there are ſome that are onely followers of his Table, and not of him; let neuer ſo little euill come vpon them, they will preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put in practiſe the counſell of that fooliſh <hi>Woman,</hi> and like vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and diſobedient chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">Iob. 2, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Blaſpheme the name of God, and dye.</hi> Let not the <hi>Shuhite</hi> then vpbraid the afflicted <hi>Iob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 3.8.</note> nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage his punniſhment as an argument of his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:183926:70"/> vnrighteouſneſſe. Thoſe eighteen perſons who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the fall of the Towers <hi>Siloam</hi> ſlew, were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſuredly greater Sinnes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the reſt that dwel in <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 13.2.</note> Let no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him therefore, that hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not ſo much as taſted the bitterneſſe of his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſay in his vants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> My holineſſe hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued me. For howſoe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiteth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſurely the Lord ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>counts him but a baſtard and cares not (it ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeem) what doth beco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of him;<note place="margin">Heb. 12, 8.</note> Did he eſteem him as a Sonne, he ſhol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:183926:70"/> not want his portion; Hee would looke more neerely to his bringing vp. With all humilitie therefore and lowlineſſe of heart, I will ſubmit my vnderſtanding and my will, with all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers and faculties of my Soule to the ſharpneſſe of his Cenſure. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our bodies cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected vs, and wee gaue them reuerence, howe much the rather ſhould we ſubiect our ſelues to the Father of Spirites, that wee may liue. They verily for a fewe daies chaſtened vs after theyr
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:183926:71"/> owne pleaſure; but tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which he doth, is for ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> profit, that we may for euer bee partakers of his holineſſe. The Fleſh w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thinke it peraduenture grieuous for the preſent, but the Spirite will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in the quiet fruite of righteouſneſſe, which afterwardes it bringeth vnto them, that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed thereby. It is a bit wherewith he Curbs the head-ſtrongneſſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our affections; and a bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, wherewith he reines them vp, from running head-long with vs into euerlaſting damnation.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:183926:71"/> Shall <hi>Dauid</hi> in the meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his minde,<note place="margin">Pſal. 141, 5</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the ſmiting of the righteous as a benefite; and his reproofes a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Oyle, that ſhall not break his head? And ſhall I thinke hardly of the Rodde of the Lord? No, no: Let him beate mee, let him bruiſe mee, let him hewe me, let him hacke mee heere in this World, ſo he ſaue me in the World to come. Let him ſtrike me heere with the <hi>Haſel-wand,</hi> ſo he caſt me not there into the boyling Cauldron. Hee maketh the wound and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:183926:72"/> bindeth it vp;<note place="margin">Iob. 5.18.</note> he ſmiteth and his handes make whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXXIII.</head>
               <p>THIS World was once a Garden, which abounded with delightes, but Man which was the Gardiner of it, neglecting both himſelfe and it, ſuffered the Plants thereof to ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot, and the fruites there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be choaked vp with weeds, ſo that now alas! It produceth nothing which is either pure or
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:183926:72"/> perfect. The Comforts of it are defectiue; and the ioyes thereof are not without their mixture. There is no Wheate in it without Darnell; no Siluer in it without droſſe. Euery Roſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hath his Thorne; and euery conueniency his diſcommodity. Health and Sickneſſe are neere Neighbors; Pleaſure &amp; Paine, thinges differing in Nature, if they be not confounded in it, they are ſurely coupled: Mirth and Melancholy heere, if we marke them well, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble one the other ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:183926:73"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:183926:73"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:183926:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:183926:74"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:183926:75"/> neerely; The ſame folds and motions of the countenance that ſerue for weeping, do likewiſe ſerue for laughter, and indeede the extreame of this dooth continually mixe it ſelfe with teares. Vertue and Vice are vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter oppoſites, yet ſtand they alwaies in each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers view, and there is nothing to bee found ſo abſolute heere belowe, but howſoeuer it haue the conſtitution of that, it will ſome way ſhowe the complexion of this; If it be faire as <hi>Rachell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 29, 17</note> it will bee tender-eyed as
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:183926:75"/> 
                  <hi>Leah;</hi> If it haue the voice of <hi>Iacob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 27, 22.</note> it will haue the handes of <hi>Eſau:</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is alwayes abſent from the full perfection. The Lord of Hoaſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered the Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> by a ſtrong and mighty hand from the ſlauery of the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 15, 25</note> but yet hee forced them to drinke the Waters of <hi>Marah;</hi> In the Deſert of <hi>Zin</hi> they wanted foode, and hee ſupplyed them with the Bread of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; hee fed them with Quailes from his owne Table; yet at <hi>Rephidim,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 16, 1.13.</note> both they, their Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:183926:76"/> and their Cattle were well-nigh killed with thirſt; and howſoeuer the Rock in <hi>Horeb</hi> did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes affoord them drinke,<note place="margin">Ibid. 17.1.</note> yet ſtill was there ſomewhat to daſh the fulneſſe of their content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">Ibid. 12.8.</note> He would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eate the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer but with ſower Hearbes; In a word, it was not at the birth of <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 21, 8.</note> but at his weaning, that <hi>Abraham</hi> made a Feaſt, to ſignify vnto vs, that while wee ſucke the breaſts of the church our Mother, our ioy is but in part, and cannot bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:183926:76"/> till the time of our admiſſion to the Table of our heauenly Father. God hath in his hand three cups, the one is full of pure Wine,<note place="margin">Pſal. 75, 9.</note> whereof the Saints that are already glorified do onely taſt; the other is full of nothing elſe but Dregs; a draught reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued onely for the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; the third is ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and is for vs that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourne heere in Houſes of Clay, the weakneſſe of whoſe condition is ſuch, as nothing in his owne ſimplicity, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue pureneſſe can fall
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:183926:77"/> within the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of our vſe. The elements which wee enioy are altered and diſguiſed. The Gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be empaired with ſom baſer ſtuffe, to fit it for our turne.<note place="margin">Heb. 5, 12.</note> Vertue it ſelfe vnleſſe it bee compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, is beyonde our ſtrength. As long as we liue in the Fleſh, we haue neede of Milke, and not of ſtrong meate. Let vs take our ſelues euen at the beſt, and alaſſe! what are we more then brittle Earth, then frailty it ſelf. Our ſight cannot endure the brightneſſe of Gods
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:183926:77"/> Maieſty, no not by refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.<note place="margin">Exo. 34, 33</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt put a vaile vpon his face, when he commeth down from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> or the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his countenaunce will daunt the eye of the Beholder. I will followe therefore after loue, and couet ſpirituall guiftes;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13, 12.</note> I will attend with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of that which is perfect. I ſee now but darkly through a Glaſſe, but then ſhall I ſee face to face; I knowe now but in part, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall I knowe, euen as I am knowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:183926:78"/>
               <head>XXXIIII.</head>
               <p>THE Eyes of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſoule, are Faith and Charity. If the right Eye be out, the left Eye ſerues but for little vſe. For without faith, good workes are not auailea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.<note place="margin">Heb. 11, 6.</note> This alone is the ground of all thinges, which are hoped for, and the euidence of thinges that are not ſeene; and without this it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to pleaſe the Lord. The Deuill, when hee fighteth with vs, neuer
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:183926:78"/> aymeth but at this. Hee knoweth, if once hee hit it, wee muſt needes giue ouer. <hi>Nahaſh</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> will haue this,<note place="margin">1. King 11.2.</note> or he will make no coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Iabeſh Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead;</hi> but let him knowe that grauntes it him, hee diſableth himſelfe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer from making Warre but to his owne excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding diſadua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage againſt his Aduerſary. For either hee muſt fight vnarmed for his owne defence, or he ſhall neither ſee how to put by the blowes of his <hi>Antagoniſt,</hi> nor how to follow his owne. The
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:183926:79"/> Eye of Faith is out, and that of Workes is ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with his Shielde. I will alwaies therefore haue a care that my Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſtrong enough on that ſide, to rebound his fiery Dartes vppon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or at the leaſt, to quench them vtterly as faſt as they come. If I perceiue it to waxe dull and dimme through the fierceneſſe of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, I will haſt mee to the Lorde, and buy of him a Salue to annoint it with,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3, 18</note> that I may ſee: hee alone is my Phiſitian, &amp; he alone ſhal cleare it by
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:183926:79"/> that enlightning power of his holy Spirite, by which hee openeth the Eies of them that ſit in darkneſſe, and in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Death. Then ſhal I bee able with bleſſed <hi>Stephen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes 7, 55.</note> euen in the heat and fury of the skirmiſh, to behold through al the heauens the glory of the Lorde, for which I doe contend, and my Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ieſus ſtanding at his right hand, ready to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour me if need require; and then with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted courage will I abide the fight, and die vpon the place, ere I giue
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:183926:80"/> ground in any fainting manner to the raging of his might. Chriſt is my ſecond, who I know wil witneſſe my valour, and reuenge my quarrell. Why ſhould I feare the powers and principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Hel? When God is with vs, who ſhal ſtand againſt vs?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXXV.</head>
               <p>BEhold (ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) the day com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth rhat ſhall flame like an Ouen,<note place="margin">Mal. 4.1.</note> and they that
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:183926:80"/> ſweare by the ſinne of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and ſay;<note place="margin">Amos 8.14</note> Thy God O <hi>Dan</hi> liueth, and the manner of <hi>Beer-She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi> liueth; yea the proud, with all ſuch as doe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly ſhall bee Stubble; the day that commeth ſhall cleane conſume them; it ſhal leaue them neither root nor branch. The Lorde will haſt him from <hi>Teman,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hab. 3.3:</note> and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one from Mount <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran:</hi> His Maieſty ſhall couer the Heauens, and the Earth ſhall be full of his glorie: Conſuming fire ſhall march before him, and burning coales
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:183926:81"/> ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe him about. Hee will ſummon all the Nations of the Earth to make their appearaunce before his Tribunall ſeat and giue to euery one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what he hath don,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.17</note> whether it be good or euill. To put the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out of al comfort, he will begin his iudgments in his owne houſe, and call euen the righteous according to that of <hi>Iob,</hi> vnto a ſtrict account of euery idle word. <hi>Thou writeſt bitter thinges</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>againſt me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 13, 26.</note> 
                  <hi>and makeſt mee poſſeſſe the iniquity of my youth; Thou putteſt my
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:183926:81"/> feete into the Stockes, and lookeſt narrowly vnto my pathes: The printes thereof are in the heeles of my feet.</hi> Now if the <hi>Caedar</hi> of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon</hi> be ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus,<note place="margin">Luke 23.31</note> what ſhal becom of the bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Wilderneſſe? If this bee doone to the greene Spring, what is remaining for the dry Stumpe? If the iuſt man be ſo hardly ſaued, wher is the hope of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? I will high me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the lord my God, with al the ſpeede I can: I will not deferre my go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him by repentance till the ſeting of the Sun;<note place="margin">Ibid. 24.25.</note>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:183926:82"/> 
                  <hi>O fooles, and ſlow of heart,</hi> ſaith he to ſuch, and will not ſtay with them but with great conſtraint. Nor will I put it of vntill the euening,<note place="margin">Ibid. 24, 37.</note> leaſt hauing found him I ſhould bee doubtfull, and think I ſee a Spirit when I looke on him. No, no, I will riſe betimes with <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 28.1.</note> and with the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Iames,</hi> will I ſeek for Ieſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the dawning of the day:<note place="margin">Prou. 8, 17.</note> Hee loueth thoſe that loue him; and they that ſeeke him early ſhal ſind him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:183926:82"/>
               <head>XXXVI.</head>
               <p>GOD is no reſpecter of perſons.<note place="margin">Ephe. 6, 9. Iohn. 4.47.</note> The Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler entreated him to come vnto his Sonne, &amp; he would not:<note place="margin">Luke 7.2.</note> The <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion</hi> did but ſende vnto him for his Seruant, and immediatly hee went. It is not the beauty of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward obiectes that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes his Eye, nor the quality of ambitious Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles that ſtirres vp his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. When he paſt thorough <hi>Iericho,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. 17, 5.</note> there were many that came
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:183926:83"/> foorth to ſee him, mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſpecious to the viewe of weaker ſence, &amp; of hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er place and ranke in the Cittie then <hi>Zacheus</hi> was yet he alone was grace by him aboue the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Ibid. 7.25.</note> The <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was not cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in ſoft rayment,<note place="margin">Math. 3.4.</note> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fed with delicates. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> meat was Locuſtes with wilde Hony, and his ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of Camels Hayre yet did hee make him greater then a Prophet <hi>Peter</hi> was not arrayed it Purple,<note place="margin">Ibid. 16.18.</note> nor did hee liue deliciouſly in Courtes of Kinges, and yet he made him Prince of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:183926:83"/> So the body bee ſound, hee cares not for the bark. If the liuing be good, let the outſide bee as ragged as it will. I wil not therefore greatly eie my preſent condition: Though I bee rich, I will not preſume vppon my wealth; though I be poore, I wil not deſpaire for my want. He that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto the Fiſher-men that were in their Ship,<note place="margin">Mat. 4.21.</note> mending their Nets, not minding him, and ſayde vnto them; <hi>Come followe me:</hi> will out of queſtion giue kind and courteous entertainment vnto him,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:183926:84"/> who out of loue, and of his owne accord, do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> humbly ſue vnto him f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his Liuery. Againe I know, that <hi>Diues</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> torments,<note place="margin">Luke 16, 23</note> when <hi>Laz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſon</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXXVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 21.28</note>
                  <hi>IVſtice</hi> is a worke when with the Lord is ſcare acquainted; It is a ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, and an alien to him he knowes not how, no which way to begin i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> In <hi>Sodom</hi> there was no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> righteous, but only <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a</hi>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:183926:84"/> or he would neuer haue waſted it with fire; none in the whole world, ſaue onely <hi>Noah,</hi> or he would neuer haue deſtroyed it with the floud. Till the Tree bee paſt hope, hee applyeth not his Axe. No, nor then but with much vnwillingneſſe and great commiſeration. He looketh at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 19.41</note> &amp; weepes to thinke on the deſtruction that ſhoulde come vpon it. He houles for <hi>Moab,</hi> he cries out for it; his heart doth mourn for them of <hi>Kirhareſeth;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 40.31.</note> He weepeth for the vine of <hi>Sibmah,</hi> as he wept for
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:183926:85"/> 
                  <hi>Iazer;</hi> he watereth <hi>Heſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bon</hi> with his teares,<note place="margin">Eſay 16.9.</note> are <hi>Elaleh</hi> is drunke with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhowers of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plain, becauſe of the deſtroye which is to fall vppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Summer fruites, &amp; vpon their Vintage. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wrath and indignatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath many Motiues t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> incite it;<note place="margin">Iob. 64 6.</note> but his mercy none. For all our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is as a filthy Cloute; wee fade like a leafe, and our iniquities like the windes doe carry vs away; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he lookes down vpon vs from the throne of his heauenly grace
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:183926:85"/> with the eye of Pitty &amp; compaſſion; he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that wee are the workemanſhippe of his handes, and in the ende, out of the zeale of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towardes vs, he crieth out;<note place="margin">Oſe, 13.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy iniquities O Iſraell, haue destroyed thee; but thy help is in me.</hi> He doth not onely tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate our imperfections, but oftentims he diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the knowledge hee hath of them; he turneth away his face, and will not ſee the ſinne becauſe he would not puniſh the Sinner. There is no daie wherein to fauour the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:183926:86"/> tranſgreſſour hee doth not breake the Tables of the Law. Our GOD is a iealous God;<note place="margin">Exod. 20, 5.</note> he viſiteth the ſinnes of the Father, vpon the Children vnto the third and fourth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of them that hate him; but ſheweth mercy vnto thouſands of them that loue him, and keepe his Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The Kingly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet therefore ſpeaking of them both, ſaieth of the one; <hi>Thy mercy, ó Lorde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 103, 11</note> 
                  <hi>is in the Heauens;</hi> and of the other; <hi>Thy Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, ô God, is like the hils,</hi> to ſignifie vnto vs, that
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:183926:86"/> his mercy doth as much exceed his iuſtice; as the high Heauens doe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount the Hils. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one is milde and ful of gentleneſſe; free from anger, and of long pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.<note place="margin">Eſay 27.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee haue ſeene the Lord,</hi> ſaid the Diſciples, but <hi>Thomas</hi> beleeues the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not; yet Chriſt forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to reproue him, and commeth not till eyght dayes after to rebuke his incredulity, and euen then, the vttermoſt of his wrath, is onely this: <hi>Put thy Fingers into my woundes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 20.26.</note> 
                  <hi>and thy hand into my ſide, and bee no longer
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:183926:87"/> faithleſse.</hi> When ſinfull <hi>Adam</hi> after his fall, had ſtoln as he imagined out of the ſight of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, idly conceiting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture, that himſelfe being hid, his fault wold not bee ſeene,<note place="margin">Gen. 3, 8.</note> God came not to correct him with a furious and haſty pace; he did but walk, and that againſt the winde, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous (as it were) to bee detained in his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges by that gentle blaſt: He walked againſt the wind ſaith the Text, not in the Morning, nor at Noone-day, but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Euening, at
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:183926:87"/> the very ſetting of the Sunne; ſo ſlow, ſo ſlack, &amp; ſo remiſſe is this deare Father of ours in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Hee dealt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with the Prodigall; hee ſawe him no ſooner comming, but his heart was ouer-ioyed, hee ran vnto him, and hauing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained him with kiſſes and kind embracements, hee calleth vnto his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants: <hi>Goe quickly, bring me forth for him the pureſt Robe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 15.22</note> 
                  <hi>kill me instantly the fatteſt Calfe, that wee may eate it, and bee merry, my Son was dead, and is aliue
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:183926:88"/> againe, loſt he was, but he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is found.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eze. 36, 25</note> So that his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours are powred ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon vs with ſome vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but his chaſtice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and his correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are diſtilled drop b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drop.<note place="margin">Cant. 5, 5.</note> My hart (ſaith he) ſhall not drop down vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by the hand of <hi>Shiſhak.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cron. 12.7.</note> He is patient, &amp; wold haue no man pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but willingly draw all men to repentaunce. I will not therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the riches of his bounty,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> and long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; he ſeekes to leade mee by it to ſaluation, nor as one that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:183926:88"/> will I diſobey the truth, and obey vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe; but I wil labour by continuance in well doing for honour, glory, and eternall life. I looke for new Heauens, and a new Earth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his promiſe,<note place="margin">Eſay 65, 17.</note> and will be therfore diligent, that I may bee found of him in peace, without ſpot, and blameleſſe.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.11.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXXVIII.</head>
               <p>PRayer is the Mindes Ambaſſador to God.
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:183926:89"/> It is the onely Agent for the Soule; but if it haue not Faith and Humility for Aſſiſtants, it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee admitted to his preſence. The one is ſo much intereſted in him, That whatſoeuer we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire when we pray,<note place="margin">Mar. 11.24</note> let vs beleeue that wee ſhall haue it, and it ſhall bee done vnto vs. The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that had ſo long bin tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bled with the fluxe, did but touch the Hem of his Garment, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our further entreatie, he turned him about, and ſaid vnto her: <hi>Daughter, be of good comfort,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 9.22.</note> 
                  <hi>thy faith
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:183926:89"/> hath made thee whole.</hi> His graces are proportioned by this.<note place="margin">Math. 9, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>According to your Faith, be it vnto you:</hi> ſaid he vnto the blinde, that came and beſought him for their ſight: And to the Captaine:<note place="margin">Math. 8, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>As thou haſt beleeued, bee it vnto thee.</hi> The other is of that excellency, might, and power, that it maketh way for our <hi>Requeſtes,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thorough the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Ayre, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands their paſſage tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the thickeſt clouds. It vſhereth them into the Priuy Chamber of his imperiall Maieſty, &amp;
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:183926:90"/> obtaines both hearing and diſpatch for them without ſtop or ſtay. The Prayer of the <hi>Centurion,</hi> ſent forth in the behalfe of his diſeaſed Seruaunt, was well accompanyed with both. <hi>I haue not found</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour of the firſt) <hi>ſuch faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 7.9.</note> 
                  <hi>no not in Iſraell;</hi> and for the laſt, it was not to be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallelled: <hi>I am vnworthy,</hi> (ſaid hee, ô humbleneſſe of mind) <hi>that thou ſhouldſt enter vnder my roofe:</hi> and by ſo ſaying, hee ſhewed himſelfe worthy, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whoſe houſe, but into whoſe heart the Lorde
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:183926:90"/> might enter. By making himſelf vnworthy (ſaith S. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi>) to receiue Chriſt into his Gates, he was made worthy to bee receiued of Chriſt into his Kingdome. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide theſe, it had with it the encouragement of Charity, that with the more aſſuredneſſe &amp; bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confidence it might appeare before him. To pray for our ſelues, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes from Nature, but to pray for others is the worke of Grace: Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity enforceth vs to that; but brotherly loue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth vs to this; And
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:183926:91"/> it is indeede a far ſweeter ſauour in the Noſtrils of the Lord, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which ariſeth from the ſenſitiue apprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our own miſery: <hi>I aduiſe you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paule</hi> to <hi>Timothy) that firſt of all Supplications,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2, 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Prayers, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſsions, and Thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuings be made for al men.</hi> The word which we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, inſtructeth vs by precepts and examples, that the conſeruation of duty to the publique, ſhould bee much more vnto vs, then the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of eyther life or being, and that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:183926:91"/> good is Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſhould be preferred before that, which is but priuate and particular.<note place="margin">Rom. 9.3.</note> S. <hi>Paule</hi> deſired to bee ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themized for his Brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren; and <hi>Moſes</hi> to bee ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed out of the Booke of life for the Children of Iſraell,<note place="margin">Exo 32, 32.</note> ſuch was their zeale vnto the Church, and ſuch their feeling of Communion. I wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually therfore labour to lift vp pure handes to Heauen without doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.<note place="margin">Luk. 18.13</note> I will imitate the lowlineſſe of the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can; and in my boſome will I cheriſh his meane
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:183926:92"/> conceite. When I pray I will not ſtand in the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 6, 6.</note> nor kneele in the corners of the ſtreets that I may bee ſeene of men; but I will enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Chamber, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſhut my doore, I wil cal vpon my heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father. He ſeeth in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and ſhal reward me openly. In my Prayers I will bee mindfull of my afflicted Bretheren, that ſo the lord may be more mindfull of mee. God is exceedingly in loue with Charity;<note place="margin">Cant. 1.1.</note> the very name thereof to him is as an oyntment powred out.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:183926:92"/> She is his onely darling; hee dooth kiſſe her with the Kiſſes of his mouth; when ſhee commeth to him, hee lodgeth her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene his breaſtes, and neuer ſendes her from him but with lade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hands. The G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oler waſhed <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſtripes,<note place="margin">Acts 16, 33</note> and by ſo doing, himſelfe was waſhed from his ſinnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XXXIX.</head>
               <p>GOdlineſſe is not a thing hereditarye, nor can true Piety be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:183926:93"/> by Legacie; an vpright heart requireth much manurance; and is not gotten but by great Husbandry.<note place="margin">Eſay 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>I had a Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>in a moſt fruitefull Hill, what could bee done, which I did not to it? Yet in the ende it brought forth nothing but ſower Grapes; in ſteade of iudgment, it gaue oppreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; in ſtead of righteouſnes it affoorded crying.</hi> The Nettle growes, where the Roſe was looked for, and out of the Egge a Chicken is expected, but beholde a Cockatrice. The ſtock is often good,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:183926:93"/> but without continuall pruning, the Plantes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate. Out of the lodge of ADAM came murderous <hi>Caine;</hi> out of the Arke of <hi>Noah,</hi> impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Cham;</hi> out of the Houſe of reuerend <hi>Eli, Ophni,</hi> and <hi>Phinees</hi> the Sonnes of <hi>Belial;</hi> out of the Court of <hi>Dauid</hi> came trayterous <hi>Abſalon;</hi> out of the Schoole of Ieſus, perfideous <hi>Iudas;</hi> &amp; out of the company of the <hi>Deacons, Nicholas</hi> the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticke. So that Vertues are not maintained by propagation; nor is a vertuous habite purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:183926:94"/> but with much ſweat; It will coſt vs the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ere we can actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſſe it as our own Free-hold. There is not an <hi>Elijah</hi> nowe to graunt ſo hard &amp; difficult a ſuite at the redoubling of his Spirite;<note place="margin">2. King 2.9</note> nor is there an <hi>Eliſha</hi> reſiding heere, that is worthy to obtaine it. I will not therefore brag that I haue <hi>Abraham</hi> for my Father, but I will la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to doe the workes of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and when I glory,<note place="margin">Iere. 9.24.</note> I will glory in this alone, that I vnderſtand &amp; know the Lord to bee the only very God, who
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:183926:94"/> ſheweth mercy, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and righteouſnes in the Earth, and Ieſus Chriſt, whom hee hath ſent to be his onely Son,<note place="margin">Luke 11.28</note> begot before all worlds, which who ſo doth, ſhal remaine for euer. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede it is not the womb that bare him; nor the Paps that gaue him ſuck which are bleſſed; but rather they that hear the word of his Father and do thereafter. Little had it auailed the <hi>Virgin</hi> to haue conceiued him in hir Wombe, or <hi>Simeon</hi> to haue receiued him in his Armes, if by the Eye
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:183926:95"/> of Fayth, they had not both perceiued, that hee was ſent from heauen to redeeme the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XL.</head>
               <p>SAthan is a bolde In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truder. Hee reſides not alwayes in the Graues, nor is hee ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byding in the Deſertes. You ſhall finde him ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the company of Gods electe and choſen Children: <hi>On a day, when they came and ſtood before the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>he likewiſe came and ſtood among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:183926:95"/> among his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; <hi>Iehoſhua,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zacha. 3.1.</note> the High Prieſt ſtandes before the Angell, and loe, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer is at his right hand to reſiſt him. Sometimes again with his Apoſtles; <hi>Haue I not choſen twelue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 6.70.</note> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and one of you is a deuil.</hi> He is a gueſt that will come without great bidding: the leaſt caſt of our eie doth ſerue him for an inuitation, &amp; the ſlighteſt compleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t will embolden him to be inſolent. If we make him our Companion, he will be preſently our Maſter. If he get but a foot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:183926:96"/> our doores, hee will caſt vs out, &amp; like a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciles diſſeiſour put vs by our right; nor ſhall it ought auaile vs to plead our Title, when hee is in poſſeſſion. I will bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies therefore verye carefull how I ſuffer him to approch me. If I canot barre him my preſence, I wil deny him my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and make him knowne by my lookes, that he ſhall not lodge in my heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:183926:96"/>
               <head>XLI.</head>
               <p>VNhallowed thoghts are the Scouts of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than. He ſildome ſuffers them to lye idle in theyr Tentes, but ſendes them alwaies forth vppon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery: Hee faſhioneth his attempts by their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſements, and as hee vnderſtandes their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, he reſtes aſſured of his own. Themſelues de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in pillage, and are therefore glad of theyr imployment. They leaue
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:183926:97"/> not a corner about the heart vnſearched, to find out an entrance. If the doores bee barred; they will aſſay to climbe the Walles, and get in at the Windowes. They doe with cunning mannage their Captaines buſines, and husband the leaſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to his beſt aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. It falleth out ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that theſe ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Aramites</hi> happen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome little Maide o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the land of <hi>Iſraell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Kings 5.2</note> to wit, ſome ſimple and vntuto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Soule, that ſtrayeth from the way of Truth, and is altogether deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:183926:97"/> of that heauenlie Conuoy of ſpiritual gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect it from the craft and fury of the Aduerſarie, and hauing ſuddainely ſurprized it, lead it away Captiue to their leprous Generall. Sometimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine theſe ſons of <hi>Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 4, 6</note> theſe wicked <hi>Bero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thites,</hi> finding the minde vnfurniſhed of a Gaurd, and ſnoaring euen at Noone with honeſt <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſheth</hi> in her owne ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, doe enter ſtealingly vpon it, and in an inſtant cut the throat of it. I wil not therefore with the
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:183926:98"/> reprobate put far awaie the euill day, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſafety to my ſelfe, where nothing can bee looked for but Death &amp; Danger. Mans life is a continual Warfare. The Prince of darkneſſe is his Enemy, who if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, hath wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to piece out the Lyons skinne; and when he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not preuaile by open battery, will neuer ſticke to compaſſe his deſignes by hidden treacherie. I wil endeauour therefore alwaies,<note place="margin">Mat. 24, 43</note> as much as in me lyeth, to bee well proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the comming of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:183926:98"/> the Thiefe: Let it bee at what houre in the night he will, he ſhall finde me wakefull, if not watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; neuer ſleeping, though ſometimes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture ſlumbring. I wil bruiſe the Serpent in the head, I will breake it in the ſhell. I wil not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a ſinfull cogitation to come to perfect groth: It ſhal die in the concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ere it neede the Cradle, poſſeſſe the Toombe. The Soule in caſes criminall (ſaith, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi>) hath the preceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of weaker fleſh; I wil driue it therefore from
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:183926:99"/> thence, that this may no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> offend.<note place="margin">Cant. 2.15.</note> I will ſtriue to catch the Foxes, the litle Foxes that deſtroy the Vines. Bleſſed (I knowe aſſuredly) is hee,<note place="margin">Pſal. 137, 9.</note> that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and daſheth theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtones.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XLII.</head>
               <p>THE life of the iuſt is a continual day. It is not troubled at any time with ſtormes, nor ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt with Cloudes, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is altogether calme and cleare. The Morning o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:183926:99"/> it is, when Chriſt the Sunne of righteouſneſſe doth ſhine out vpon the heart of one regenerate, and by the influence of his beames doth ſcatter &amp; diſpierce thoſe miſtie vapours and exhalations of ignorance &amp; ſtinking errour, which Sathan himſelfe had belched forth to hinder the ſoule from finding out the way of truth: the noon ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is that hourely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe and aſcent of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall grace, which brings them to the <hi>Zenith</hi> of all true perfection. <hi>The way of the godly ſhineth as the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:183926:100"/> light</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the Morne:<note place="margin">Prou. 4, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>It en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth more and more vnto the perfect day,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the Noone. After the iuſtification of wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Sinners by the Law of Faith, there is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued augmentation &amp; ſupply of guifts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their mindes are by degrees made fitter for the knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the loue of GOD, and by which afterwards they are enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>Children of the light, and Children of the day.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.3</note> They are gone out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and dwell now in
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:183926:100"/> the Land of <hi>Goſhen:</hi> they neede no Torch-light to direct their ſteps: there is a pillar of celeſtiall fire in their boſome, which like a Taper giueth light vnto their feete, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them treade aright the paths of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements. But alas! With the wicked it is nothing ſo. Their waies are as the darkneſſe, nor do they know into what daungerous places they may fal.<note place="margin">Iob. 5.14.</note> They meet with blindneſſe in the Morne, and grope at noone as in the night: they feele for the wall,<note place="margin">Eſay 59.10</note> as men that had
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:183926:101"/> no Eyes; and in the day their feet doe ſtumble as in the twilight. The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Luminaries to them are alwaies in Eclipſe, &amp; the leſſer ſo obſcured as help them little or not at all. I will ſtudy therefore continually, for holines, for pureneſſe, and ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety. The night is paſt, the day is come,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.12</note> and nowe will I caſt away the workes of darkneſſe, and put on the Armour of light. I will cloath my ſelfe with the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; take no thoght at all to ſatisfie the luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſires of the Fleſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:183926:101"/>
               <head>XLIII.</head>
               <p>THe true Souldiour of Chriſt is known by nothing better then this valour. He that is faint and of a fearefull Spirit, is but a falſe vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of that name.<note place="margin">Deut. 20.8.</note> The Lord of hoaſts will none of ſo ſoft an edge, of ſuch an yeilding temper vnder his pay.<note place="margin">Cant. 3, 8.</note> Thoſe of his band are ſtrong and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aliant; they all handle the Sword, and are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in warre; euery one hath his Fauchion on his
<pb facs="tcp:183926:102"/>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:183926:103"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:183926:103"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:183926:104"/> Thigh for the feare by night. They ſee the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> for which they fight before them, and had rather die one foot forwards, then adde many years to their life by one foote of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traite. They had rather faile in good and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ends for the publike, then obtaine all that can be wiſhed &amp; deſired for themſelues in their own proper Fortune. The mouth of Wiſdom hath taught them, that <hi>A good heart is a continuall Feaſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 15.15.</note> and that the Conſcience of good intentions in
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:183926:104"/> themſelues, let their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe be what it will, is a more continuall ioy to Nature, then all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke prouiſion a man can make, for ſtill ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and peaceable repoſe. Such as haue wedded their affections to theyr owne particular; or any way betrothed them to the things of this world, and are backwardes ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that, or other like reſpectes in the haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding of their life and liuing, he vtterly caſhie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. <hi>Gideon</hi> before hee doth encounter with the <hi>Midianites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 7, 3.</note> diſcardes the
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:183926:105"/> Cowards at Mount <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead,</hi> &amp; cleareth his camp of al ſuch crackt and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken courages as fall to pieces before the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of their enemy. So likewiſe <hi>Iudas Maccabeus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Macca. 3.56.</note> before he meete the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Antiochus</hi> at <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maus,</hi> proclaimes a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſcharge to euery pale and milky liuer tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout his Army and with all willingnes doth licenſe their departure. I will at no time therefore giue place to any timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conceit, but fortifie my heart with ſuch a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and vnſhaken confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:183926:105"/> that Afflictio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, come ſhe neuer ſo hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſguiſed, ſhall not appale me. The Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is my Generall, and the hire of my valour a Crowne of immortall glory. Baſe were the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, that would not wiſh to dye vnder the conduct of ſo braue a Prince, for the purchaſe of ſo great a price. Hee maketh himſelfe my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, and marketh out the way that I muſt march with the precious bloud, that guſheth out of his owne wounds. He calleth me after him, and
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:183926:106"/> I will ſurely follow. No Death, nor Hell, ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> driue me to a ſtand: I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuffer with him in th conflict, that I may ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with him in the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XLIIII.</head>
               <p>TO murmure again God argueth a w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Grace; and to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Affliction, ſheweth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect of heauenly conſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Eccl. 10, 26</note> He that hath kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge and is well inſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, will vndergoe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> croſſe with patience, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:183926:106"/> neither ſtamp nor ſtorm to ſee himſelfe reformed. The Lord (he knoweth) when hee ſhootes his Darts, doth leauell high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then at the downefall of a wretched Sinner; and that howſoeuer hee bruiſe him, it is not with a Rod of Iron;<note place="margin">Pſal. 2, 9.</note> howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he break him, it is not like a Potters veſſell, but as the Gold-Smith doth his Plate, to melt and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion it anewe. The Faſt is as delightful to him as the Feaſt, and the Vigile as welcome as the Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day it ſelfe. Hee doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme no otherwiſe of
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:183926:107"/> this Worlde, then of an outward place,<note place="margin">1. King. 6.7</note> in which the hard &amp; ſtony mindes of ſuch as God affecteth, muſt be hammered and poliſhed by the hands of Aduerſity and Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, before they can bee fit to ſet in the Temple of that newe <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> which is erected by one of greater power and Maieſty then <hi>Salomon.</hi> But alaſſe! The heart of the fooliſh cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of this. 'Tis like the Wheele of a Cart; the vaue thereof is not moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened with the Oyle of the Spirit,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 33, 6</note> and doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:183926:107"/> therefore, but creak vnder the burthen. It is a veſſell, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede is void of all good vertues and abilities: It runneth only on the lees, let God but ſtrike it with his hand, and the ſounde it giueth, will be the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of his emptineſſe. In a word, it is an Earthen Pipkin, which wanting liquor in it,<note place="margin">Wiſ. 1.11.</note> is ready to cracke in pieces when it feeles the flame. I will beware therfore of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, which auaileth nothing. The eare of iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie heareth all things, and the noiſe of him that<note place="margin">Num. 11, 1.</note>
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:183926:108"/> muttereth and repineth ſhall not bee hid. The Children of Iſraell were conſumed with the Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Lord,<note place="margin">Ibid. 14, 30.</note> for their vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iuſt complaintes: He would ſuffer none of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to enter into the Land of Promiſe, ſaue onel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Caleb</hi> the Son of <hi>Ieph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nah,</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua</hi> the ſonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Nun.</hi> Whatſoeue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> therefore it ſhall plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his will to lay vpon me my will ſhall not refu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to beare it. I cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> conſcience but ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſomewhat for his ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that indured ſo much f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine. Let him deal wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:183926:108"/> me therefore as he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good, I will hold my toong with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> and keepe ſilence, becauſe it is his doing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XLV.</head>
               <p>VErtue is great in grace and eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the king of heauen: they that embrace it are his onely fauorites. Hee dooth affect them won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully, and vſeth them at all times with great familiarity. Fiue hunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſixty fiue yeares did
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:183926:109"/> 
                  <hi>Henoch</hi> walke with him vppon the earth,<note place="margin">Gen. 5, 24.</note> and ſo delighted him with the ſoftneſſe of his carriage, and the ſweetneſſe of his conuerſation, that hee took him wholly to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and of a <hi>Penſioner,</hi> made him one of his Chamber. Hee ſent a Charret of Fire from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, to fetch <hi>Elijah</hi> to him,<note place="margin">2. Kin. 2.11</note> and appointed a Guard of glorious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to attend it: hee did ſo long to enioy his com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany, that Death hee thought would bee to ſlow a Meſſenger to giue his deſires a ſpeedy ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:183926:109"/> &amp; contentment, and did therefore ſend a Whirlewinde foorth to haſten his arriuall: The Lord is exceeding tender ouer the godly: he will preſerue his body as the Apple of his eye; he wil ſhield his ſoule from the power of the graue. The wickedneſſe of Man in former times was grown to ſuch a height, and his minde ſo deepely rooted in all euill, that GOD grew ſorry hee had euer made him, and was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to deſtroy both him and all thinges elſe from of the Earth; but when
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:183926:110"/> he thought vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpright <hi>Noah,</hi> great was the care he took for the ſafety &amp; preſeruation both of him and his. He doth impart his ſecrets to the iuſt,<note place="margin">Eſay 41, 8.</note> and taketh the righteous for his boſome friendes. He would not hide from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> that which hee meant to doe to <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ah.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 18, 17.</note> And when the Patriarke had begun to intercede for them, could but tenne perſons haue been found vntain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with that foule cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, wherewith the inhabitants of thoſe two places were ſo generally
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:183926:110"/> infected, he would haue ſpared them all at his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty for their ſakes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: as hee did <hi>Zoar</hi> at poore <hi>Lots</hi> requeſt:<note place="margin">Gen. 19.21.</note> ſo eaſily doth hee ſubſcribe to the petitions and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of them that are ſounde and pure in heart. Let who ſo liſteth therefore ambitiouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the countenance of worldly <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> I and my Thoughtes wil ſerue the Lord. One day with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Courtes is better then a thouſande other where;<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.10.</note> and I would ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner chooſe to be a door<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper in the Houſe of
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:183926:111"/> my God, then to dwell in the tabernacles of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faine Impiety.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14, 7.</note> They tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reſt vnder his ſhaddowe ſhall reuiue as the Corn and flouriſh as the Vine: their beauty ſhall bee as the Oliue-Tree, &amp; their ſmell as <hi>Lebanon:</hi> But they that rely vppon the breath of man, their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhal vaniſh as the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Dewe, and as the ſmoak that goeth out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Chimney. I will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon therefore with <hi>Moſes,</hi> the delicates of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Table, to bee a Partner in all diſaſtrous accidents with the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:183926:111"/> of Iſraell, and deſire rather to lye at the gates of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and be a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer in the afflictions of my diſtreſſed Bretheren, then ſtand with <hi>Hamon</hi> at the Kings elbow. Heere now is Grace, and by &amp; by a graue: but loue and honour commeth there in the riere-warde of all trouble.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XLVI.</head>
               <p>MAns heart is like a Houſe; the cloſer he keepeth it, the worſe it is: The doores &amp; win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:183926:112"/> of it, muſt by a true confeſſion of his ſins bee ſet wide open to the Lord, that by the beames of his enlightning Spirit, the roomes thereof may be well ayred, and euery corner of it ſweetned, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the comming of his Sauiour and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. <hi>Open to me, my Siſter, my Loue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 5, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>my Doue,</hi> (ſayd Chriſt vnto his Spouſe, and in the Reuelation, <hi>I ſtand at the doore &amp; knock if any Man open,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 3, 20</note> 
                  <hi>I will com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in vnto him, and will ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> with him, and he with me.</hi> He carrieth a good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion &amp; conceit, of thoſe
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:183926:112"/> that are ready at the gate to giue him entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or that at the leaſt no ſooner heare him, but with the greateſt ſpeede they let him in; hee will miniſter comfort and conſolation vnto them, that by repentance make knowne vnto him theyr cares and grieuaunces. But ſuch as will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his voice, nor make him entrance when he calleth at the firſt, do but awaken his iealouſy, and giue him cauſe to doubt, that all is not wel within; They haue aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly ſome <hi>Vnder-ſitters,</hi>
                  <pb n="196" facs="tcp:183926:113"/> that dare not abide the preſence of authority, &amp; either for that, or ſome ſuch like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration are ſlacke in his admiſſion. I will confeſſe therefore againſt my ſelfe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.5.</note> my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe vnto the Lord, and hee ſhall forgiue the forfeiture of my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes;<note place="margin">Pro. 28.13.</note> I wil diſcouer to him mine iniquities, and he ſhall cleanſe me from all vnrighteouſnes: who ſo hideth his tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhall neuer proſper; but hee that confeſſeth and forſaketh them, ſhal bee ſure of mercy. The Thiefe before the Iudge
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:183926:113"/> approach, doth conuay out of his owne cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, euen euery trifling thing, the poſſeſſion whereof he cannot iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to be lawfull, I will imitate him in this, and before ſuch time as death ſhall come to apprehend me, I wil clear my hart of whatſoeuer may be any way ſuſpected;<note place="margin">Eccl. 17, 27</note> Whilſt I liue, and am in health, I will diſcloſe my faultes and imperfections to the Lord; I will giue him an inuentarie of my workes and weakneſſes,<note place="margin">Prou. 16, 3.</note> that by ſo doing, my thoughtes may be eſtabliſhed. If I
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:183926:114"/> perceiue at any time that my conſcience hath ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited vpon the ſeeming ſweetes and pleaſures of this World,<note place="margin">Eccl. 13, 21</note> I wil accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Wiſe-mans counſell, ariſe, goe out, and vomit, that then I may take my reſt, &amp; keep my Soule from ſickneſſe and diſtemperature. The guilt of Sinne is an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtume in the minde; If I feele it in my boſom, I will apply that to it, which may draw the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption to the outward partes; If it breake with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, it endaungereth the life, but if the rupture of
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:183926:114"/> it chance without, there may be hope of recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. I will vnwrap the Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of my ſoule, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to the viewe of Chriſt, that hee may heale them. Vnleſſe I do acquaint him with my burthen, how can I hope to bee refreſhed by him?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XLVII.</head>
               <p>THE hart of the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh is a broken Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell;<note place="margin">Eccl. 21, 14.</note> Charity will none of it; It is not a Potſhard that will ſerue her turne. <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lorde thy God</hi> (ſaith ſhe)<note place="margin">Luke 10, 27</note> 
                  <hi>with al
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:183926:115"/> thy Soule, and withall thy Thought, and withall thy Might.</hi> Such as vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand haue ſworn allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to Hypocriſie, and are in minde the ſeruants of Impoſture, cannot endure to heare of this. They will deuide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into ſeuerall por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 10, 2.</note> &amp; what the world doth leaue, they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath to God, makes no ſcruple if neede require, to holde a Candle for their owne aduantage, both to <hi>Michaell</hi> and the Serpent.<note place="margin">Mat. 17.15.</note> They are like that Lunatik in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; one while they fall
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:183926:115"/> into the Fire, another while they ſlip into the Water: And hence it is, that they be neither hot nor colde; by reaſon whereof the Lord ſo vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſtaſteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he will ſpue them out of his mouth,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3, 16</note> and ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſlide continually from bad to worſe, till in the end, as men not ſenſible of their eſtate, they dye impenitent, and not ſo much as toucht with any deteſtation or diſlike of their fore-paſt enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. They ſtand in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of warmth, which doth embolden Sathan
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:183926:116"/> to aſſaile them; he neuer feareth to bee midling with them in this med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſtate: but were they thoroughly heated with the flames of a ſincere and vndiſguiſed zeale, as they ought to bee, hee would not dare once to come neere them. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth the Fly, which neuer ſetleth it ſelfe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſeething pot, but is alwaies exceeding bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, where there is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency of heate. Hee that contentes himſelfe with the Water of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 3, 16.</note> and doth not ſeeke to be baptized of Chriſt with
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:183926:116"/> fire and the Holy-ghoſt, is made the only But and ſcope of his attempts. It is not therefore a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall ayring that ſhall ſatisfy my cold deſires; I will ſo heate them in the well-kindeled flames of true Deuotion, that like a ſearing-Iron, hee ſhall no ſooner ſtretch out his hand to touch mee, but I will brand him for his bolde preſumption, and for euer after make him ſo fearefull of mee, that when hee ſeeth me, though at neuer ſo great a diſtance, he ſhall come creeping towardes mee
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:183926:117"/> like a Spaniell with his belley on the ground, he ſhall cry out to me with an extended voice, and ſay;<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke 5.7</note> 
                  <hi>What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to do with thee, thou Seruant of the moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igh GOD? I charge thee by thy Lorde and may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that thou torment mee not.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XLVIII.</head>
               <p>THe Croſſe of Chriſt is that Rod of <hi>Moſes,</hi> by which the Deuil, that ſpirituall <hi>Pharaoh</hi> is ſtrooke with ſuch diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of plagues, that at
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:183926:117"/> the laſt he is enforced to driue from him, thoſe which er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> while he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>old haue draw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. It is a glorious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall monument, ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted as a Trophy by the hand of Victory, to the diſhonour and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that oppreſſor and inſulting Tyrant. Hee ſtandes aloofe, and ſtares vpon it with an enuious eie, but is affraid to draw neere vnto it, leaſt hee and his temptations might chance to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured by it, as were by that the Serpents of the Enchanters. It is that
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:183926:118"/> bleſſed Tree, with the boughs whereof the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Marah</hi> were made ſweete: It altereth the bitterneſſe of Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and makes the Cup of the Lord, which of it ſelfe is exceeding ſharpe, delightful to the taſt:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.10.</note> 
                  <hi>I take pleaſure</hi> (ſayth Saint <hi>Paule) in all reprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and perſecutions for his ſake;</hi> &amp; the Apoſtles, after they had been bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the appointment of the Counſell at <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 5, 41.</note> departed thence with cheerefull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, reioycing that they were reputed wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:183926:118"/> to ſuffer rebuke for his Name. It is that princely Scepter of <hi>Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhueroſh,</hi> which beeing ſtretched out, dooth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe our approach vnto the Throne of his Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Grace. It is that key of the Kingly Prophet, which hath opened vnto vs the greateſt miſteries, and the profoundeſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets that were euer heard of. It is that ladder of the Patriark, by which our paſſage inro heauen is eaſier nowe, then euer it was before. In a word, it is that golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke, in which the life
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:183926:119"/> and light of men was ſet,<note place="margin">Iohn 1, 4.</note> whoſe brightneſſe was ſo great, that the <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion</hi> by meanes thereof, euen through the <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> darkneſſe of thoſe times, was able to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his Diuinitie, when oppreſt with feare, hee cryed out and ſaid; <hi>True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this was the Sonne of the liuing God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 27.52</note> I wil not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reioice in any thing,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> but in the Croſſe of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, by which the World is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified vnto me, &amp; I vnto the world. Night &amp; day will I make it the ſubiect of my Meditation; and
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:183926:119"/> ſo I may attaine to the knowledge of this,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.2</note> I will not eſteeme of any other wiſedome whatſoeuer. What doctrine is it, which is not heere com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized? His paſſion is the Epilogue of all. There is not any thing, either in Heauen or in Earth, but as the Apoſtle ſaieth, is recapitulated to the full in Chriſt.<note place="margin">Ephe. 1, 10.</note> Mount <hi>Caluary</hi> ſhall therefore bee my Schoole, and the Booke which I will reade, ſhall bee the lanched ſide, and bloudy boſome of my bleſſed Sauiour. I will thinke vpon his wounds;
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:183926:120"/> I will conſider his skars; &amp; the prints of the nails, ſhall bee as breathing-ſtops to helpe my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XLIX.</head>
               <p>AS Siluer droſſe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Potſhard, ſo are burning lips,<note place="margin">Pro. 26.23.</note> and an euill heart. Hee tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dwelleth in the Heauen doth abhorre it, and wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for euer haue it in deriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It is not complement that pleaſeth him. The Kinges Daughter was al glorious within,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45, 13.</note> or little
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:183926:120"/> would the Lorde haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed her ſumptuous cloathing of Broidered Gold. If the in-ſide of the Veſſel be not cleane, let the out-ſide bee as glorious as it will, our GOD will none of it. The Figge-Tree was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull to the Eye, but yet it could not eſcape the curſe. He wold haue nothing ſeem that which it is not. <hi>Eyther make the Tree good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 12.33.</note> 
                  <hi>and his fruite good</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>or the Tree euill, and his fruite euill;</hi> worſhip either God or <hi>Belial,</hi> and halt no longer betweene two opinions.
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:183926:121"/> For one to haue the <hi>Voyce of Iacob,</hi> and the <hi>handes of Eſau,</hi> is a degree of Hypocriſie beyonde his knowledge, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and conceite. The thought of it doot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cleane amaze him; <hi>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> can you ô ye viperous bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> when your ſelues are i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly nothing elſe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> filth and putrifaction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>vtt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thinges that are of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring constitution? For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the abundance of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> heart, the mouth ſpeaket<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> So that in vain it is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, <hi>Maiſter, Maiſter,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe withall we doe the thinges which hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth.
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:183926:121"/> Our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe muſt exceede that of the Scribes and Phariſes,<note place="margin">Math. 5, 20.</note> or we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen. I will not therefore be like the blinde and lame, that ſit begging at the entrance of a Citty, and ſhew the way to them that paſſe along, but ſet no foote in it themſelues; I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company them my ſelfe vnto the place; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies as neere as I can, countenaunce a godly precept with a good pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent. The word of the Lord is called a Sword;
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:183926:122"/> 
                  <hi>Take the Sword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 6, 16.</note> 
                  <hi>which is the word o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God;</hi> It cannot bee em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed but by the hand And hence it is, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſundry places of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scriptures we read in the originall, that it was i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the handes of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; as namely, in the hand of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 20, 2.</note> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hand of <hi>Haggai,</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hand of <hi>Malachi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 1.1.</note> &amp;c. t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſignify vnto vs, that the inſtructions which we giue our brethren, ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not conſiſt ſo much i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wordes, as in workes an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good examples. He tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can doe that, which hee
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:183926:122"/> ſaieth, hee alone is that <hi>Salt of the Earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5, 13.</note> which ſhall neuer looſe his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour; hee alone is that <hi>Citty on a Hell,</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be hid; in a word, he alone is that <hi>Candle in the Candlesticke,</hi> which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth light to all that are about it, and ſhineth out ſo clearely and ſo bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they which ſee it cannot but glorifye the Lord which is in heauen. I will continually there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo ſpeake, and ſo do,<note place="margin">Iames 2.12</note> as one that looketh to be iudged by the Law of Liberty. Chriſt Ieſus hath left me an example,<note place="margin">Ioh 13 15.</note>
                  <pb n="216" facs="tcp:183926:123"/> that I ſhould do, euen as hee that hath done, and ſurely I will ſtriue to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe it in all thinges, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did that patterne, which was ſhewed him in the Mount.<note place="margin">Exo. 25, 40.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>L.</head>
               <p>THe World abounds with men of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and depraued minds; It is the harbour of head-ſtrong Rebelles, which haue ſworne the downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall and deſtruction of true <hi>Piety;</hi> and much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:183926:123"/> ſhe hath to finde one angle out in al this ſpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Round, in which ſhe may reſt ſecure from their aſſaſſinous &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering handes. A vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deede cannot eſcape the forked tongue of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous <hi>Detraction,</hi> nor a good intention finde paſſage for it ſelfe, but with exceeding oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3, 8</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi> ſhal no ſooner goe about to diſcharge their dutyes, but <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres</hi> will bee ready to reſiſt them:<note place="margin">1. King. 22 11.</note> the <hi>Baalites</hi> will continually be buſy with <hi>Elijah:</hi> and plain <hi>Micheas</hi>
                  <pb n="218" facs="tcp:183926:124"/> ſhall no ſooner ſtirre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,<note place="margin">Nehe. 2.19</note> but <hi>Zidkijah</hi> will bee butting at him with his Iron hornes. Where Chriſt is, there are the Phariſes; where <hi>Simon Peter</hi> is, there likewiſe is <hi>Simon Magus;</hi> and where Saint <hi>Paule</hi> is, there are the falſe Apoſtles, that what the right hand of the Lord doth raiſe, the left hand of the Deuill may deſtroy. Whilſt our abiding place is here, we ſhall alwaies meete with many rubs and lets to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt the ſmoothneſſe of our courſe in iuſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedinges: but this ſhall
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:183926:124"/> not abate my reſolution: I will ſtriue to franchiſe and ſurmount al difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: Nor Sinne, nor Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than ſhall ſo ſtrongly barricado vp my paſſage, but by the aſſiſtaunce of the holy Spirite I will make thorough them to my aymes.<note place="margin">Phil. 2, 13.</note> Hee that wrought in mee the <hi>Wil,</hi> ſhall likewiſe worke in me the <hi>Deede;</hi> and as he gaue me the grace to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, ſo ſhall he grant me the power to goe on. I am freede from the yoke of bondage, and now,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.</note> nor death, nor life, nor Angels, nor principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:183926:125"/> nor powers; nor things preſent, nor thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeperate mee from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>LI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIſedome</hi> is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary State and Dignitie,<note place="margin">Prou. 9, 3.</note> many honourable Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins doe continually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend het. She hath hew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out her houſe of ſeauen pillers, and hath ſent out
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:183926:125"/> her Maides to call men to the wals and Towers of her Citty; but there are ſome that wil not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to haue their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage made by them: they are they ſay, inſpired fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, and as <hi>Elijah</hi> was fed by Crowes, ſo are they by Angels, not with meate nor breade, but with a hidden kind of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial <hi>Manna.</hi> They ſcorn thoſe groſſer introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſchool <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and thinke they cannot admire Gods power and authority as they ought, if in things Deuine they ſhuld attribute any force
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:183926:126"/> to human reaſon.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14</note> Their vſuall diſcourſes are, <hi>The natural man, not the things that are of God, for they are fooliſhneſſe to him: he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned;</hi> and <hi>That the Lord hath threatned to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Wiſedome of the wiſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cor. 1, 19</note> 
                  <hi>and to caſt away the vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtanding of the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi> Againe, the word and preaching of S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay they, ſtood not in the enticing ſpeech of man,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2, 4.</note> but in plaine euidence of the Spirit, and of power. What ſhould we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do but vtterly aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:183926:126"/> thoſe needleſſe Arts and Sciences,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2, 8</note> which are (as the Apoſtle ſaith) the rudiments of the world, and not after Chriſt? As if the way to bee ripe in faith, were to be rawe in wit and iudgement, as if reaſon were an enemye to Religion, Childiſh ſimplicity, the Mother of diuine ſufficiency. The name of the <hi>Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> is growne hatefull to them, the <hi>Star of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> is no better thoght of, then if it were a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtrous and vnlucky Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met; or as if God had ſo accurſed it, that it ſhould
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:183926:127"/> neuer ſhine out in things concerning our dutye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way toward him, but bee eſteemed as the Star of <hi>Remphan,</hi> or as that in the <hi>Reuelation</hi> called <hi>Worme-wood,</hi> which bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fallen from Heauen, maketh Riuers and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Waters,<note place="margin">Reuel. 8, 10</note> into which it falleth ſo bitter that men in taſting them do dye therof. The word of GOD (ſay they) is a two edged Sword, as for the Weapon of naturall Reaſon, it is as the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of <hi>Saul,</hi> rather cumberſome about the Souldier of Chriſt, then
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:183926:127"/> needful, wheras indeed it is, as that which ſlew <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah,</hi> if they bee as <hi>Dauid</hi> was, that vſe it. Poyſon may com fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out a Roſe, and out of Hemlocke Honie may bee drawne; but then a Spyder muſt not ſucke the one, nor a Bee the other. I will not therefore be affrayde to imitate the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> who at their going out from amongſt the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> took from them all the Gold and Siluer that they could, &amp; afterwards made a Tabernacle of it to God in the deſert; nor <hi>Salomon,</hi> who refuſed not
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:183926:128"/> to accept both Woode and Workemen, Caedar, and Firre from the hands of <hi>Hiram</hi> king of <hi>Tyre,</hi> for the erecting of a houſe vnto the Name of the Lorde his God. There is in the world no kinde of knowledge, whereby a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of truth is ſeene, but wee iuſtly account it precious; and that prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall trueth in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof all other knowledge is vile, may receiue from it ſom kind of light. So that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be that Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Wiſedome of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and <hi>Caldeans,</hi>
                  <pb n="227" facs="tcp:183926:128"/> wherewith <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> were ſo richly furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: or that Naturall, Morall, and Ciuill wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Graecians, which the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did bring from <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus:</hi> or that Iudaicall, which he learned ſitting at the feet of <hi>Gamaliell,</hi> I will by no means detract from the dignity therof, leaſt by ſo doing, I ſhuld iniure euen God himſelf who beeing that light, which none can aproach, hath ſent out theſe lights whereof we are capable, euen as many ſparckles reſembling the bright
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:183926:129"/> Fountaine from whych they riſe. That the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vſe and application of prophane authoritie, can bee no preiudice to ſacred Writ; howſoeuer therefore I drinke of the Waters of life with Chriſt, yet will I not let as occaſion ſerueth, to drawe at the Well with the <hi>Samaritan.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>LII.</head>
               <p>THe Pride of a man ſhal bring him low, but the humble in Spirit ſhall enioy glorie,
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:183926:129"/> He that delighteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his own greatnes, and when hee vieweth the ſtatelineſſe of his high-built Palaces, doth vaunt out of a ſwelling Spirit with <hi>Nebuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan, 4, 27</note> 
                  <hi>Is not this great Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel that I haue built for the houſe of the Kingdome, by the might of my power, and for the glory of my maieſty?</hi> A voyce from Heauen ſhall tell him preſently, that he ſhall bee vtterlie depriued of the ſocietie and commerce of men, and bee enforced to take vp his dwelling with the
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:183926:130"/> Beaſts of the fielde. Hee that ſhal ſay in his heart, <hi>I will aſcend vp into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 14.13,</note> 
                  <hi>and exalt my Throne aboue beſide the ſtarres. I will ſit vppon the mount of the congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſides of the North; I will climbe aboue the height of the cloudes, and I will bee lyke the moſt High;</hi> He ſhal be thrown with Lucifer the ſonne of the Morning, downe into the loweſt pit. And to him that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth on the multitud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of his merits, it ſhall bee ſayd,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3, 17</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſayeſt I am rich, and increaſed with goodes, and haue neede of nothing:
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:183926:130"/> and knoweſt not that thou art wretched, and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and poore, and blinde, and naked.</hi> The Publican did neuer boaſte of his vprightneſſe, nor did he brag of his tything Mint and Cumin, yet hee was iuſtified, when the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe,</hi> notwithſtanding his former purity, was clean reiected. Hee that is proude, is like a <hi>Glow-worme,</hi> hee carryeth an outward ſhew of pomp and glory in the darknes of this worlde, but in the day of iudgement, when Chriſt the Sun of Iuſtice ſhall appeare, hee ſhall
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:183926:131"/> looſe his luſter, and hys light ſhall ſeeme as if it were extinct. The eye of <hi>Ignorance</hi> may highly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue him, but the touch will ſhewe him to bee counterfait and baſe. Let who ſo liſteth therefore go ſettle his ambition in the Plaines of <hi>Sennaar;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 11, 2</note> let him depart with wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and voluptuous Worldlinges from the Eaſt, and ſeeke to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe a name vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe elſe-where; there is a Star, which calleth me thither ward, and I will follow it, till I come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Maunger, where
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:183926:131"/> the meanneſſe of my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours byrth ſhall make me cal to mind the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mine owne. I will obſerue the lowly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that bleſſed Lambe, and with the thought of his humility giue life to mine. There is nothing in mee that is ought, which I haue not receiued. When I ſhall therefore offer vppe my heart vnto the Lorde, I will bury all preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the apprehenſion of humane weaknes, and high conceits ſhall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh in the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my owne vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe.
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:183926:132"/> It is a Turtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Feathers of it muſt be plucked off,<note place="margin">Leuit. 1.16</note> and the maw thereof pulled out, and caſt vppon the Eaſt ſide of the Aultar, in the place of the aſhes, or god will not accept it for a Sacrifice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>LIII.</head>
               <p>SInne is a great bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, the weight thereof did cracke in ſunder the very heauens, and through the bowels of the earth did force a paſſage to the loweſt he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="235" facs="tcp:183926:132"/> It broke the backe of all the creatures, and made as I may ſay, <hi>Nature</hi> her ſelfe to hault. There was no part in all this vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall <hi>Frame,</hi> but was tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly bruiſed, if not broken. All things were vtterly diſioynted vvith the fal. The <hi>Sphears</hi> were put beſide their purer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, &amp; the Elements ſo confounded with the violence of the ſhocke, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and inbred motion the Fire came down and burnt <hi>Pentapolis;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 7, 17</note> the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter roſe vp, and drowned the Worlde. There was
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:183926:133"/> not any thing could bee found ſo ſtiffe or ſtrong which did not yeild. The euerlaſting Mountaynes were ſhiuered,<note place="margin">Hab. 3.6.</note> and the auncient hilles did bow. Yea, God himſelfe, who ſate til then vnmoueable vppon the ſquare baſe of his Mercy,<note place="margin">Gen. 3, 8</note> and tooke no care but how to pleaſure vs, did then ariſe out of his ſeat, &amp; with the foot of Iuſtice meaſured the walkes of <hi>Paradice.</hi> The Earth did ſink vnder the ſinne of <hi>Dathan</hi> &amp; <hi>Abir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> as too weake a prop for ſuch an vnſupportable loade:<note place="margin">Num. 16, 32</note> And ſo indeede it
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:183926:133"/> doth euen vnder vs. For what are our Graues &amp; Sepulchres, but ſo many proofes and witneſſes of the heauineſſe thereof: but for which, the verie waters would haue been able to haue ſuſtained vs as they did Chriſt our Sauiour. But this alas! is nowe; In the day of Iudgment <hi>it ſhal be vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly broken, it ſhall bee cleane diſſolued;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ſa. 24, 20</note> 
                  <hi>it ſhal reel too &amp; fro like a drunken man, and ſhall be remoued like a tent, the iniquitie thereof ſhall be heauy vpon it, ſo that it ſhall fall, and riſe no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To him therefore that
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:183926:134"/> came into the World t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> help the Lame, will I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com while the time doth ſerue, an humble ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.5.</note> and beſeech him ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, that hee woulde vouchſafe to cure my Cripple ſpirit, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, eaſe it of that grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous fardle vnder which it groaneth, that ſo I may be able to walke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in the path of Gods commaundements. The way to Heauen is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſteep, I muſt be free from all encumbraunce, or I can make no expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="239" facs="tcp:183926:134"/>
               <head>LIIII.</head>
               <p>WOrldly pleaſure is the bane of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly contemplatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; and a minde diſtracted with many thinges, cannot mind as it ought that one thing which is neceſſary. The bleſſed virgin during the time of her painefull flight, did neuer want the company of her beloued Son; hee was continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with her, whilſt ſhee liued as an exile in the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but when ſhe went vp to <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to the feaſt,<note place="margin">Luke 2.42.</note> ſhee loſt him preſently. As long
<pb n="340" facs="tcp:183926:135"/> as the <hi>Theſbite</hi> remained in the ſolitary Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he was deliciouſly fed by the Lordes owne hand, but when he made his repaire to populous and frequented places, his wantes grewe ſuch, that a poore Widdowe was faine to releeue him with a peece of bread Our God is the GOD of peace; he wil not abide in a tumultuous breaſt. His Tabernacle is in <hi>Shalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 76.2.</note> and his dwelling in <hi>Zio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Hee would not ſet foote vpon the earth, til all the Nations of the ſame had linked themſelues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:183926:135"/> in loue and amitie, &amp; that a friendly compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition was made the peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od of all hoſtile differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. His Image can no more bee ſeene in an vnſetled hart, then the ſhaddowe of a man in troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. We muſt calme the bluſtrig motions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemperatures of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, or wee ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enioy the ſweetneſſe of ghoſtly conſolation. The Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> did receiue no <hi>Manna,</hi> till they had paſt the raging Sea,<note place="margin">Actes 2.2</note> and were come into the quiet deſert. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were ſitting in a
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:183926:136"/> Chamber priuately, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they receiued the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter;<note place="margin">1 King. 19, 12.</note> and <hi>Elijah</hi> ſtood alone in the entring of a Caue, when the Lorde not in a tempeſtuous whirlewind, nor in a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Earthquke, nor in a ſtorme of fire, but in a ſoft and gentle ſound ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared vnto him, who thereuppon couered his face immediatly with his Cloake, that nothing might withdraw his ſight from the full beholding of ſuch ineſtimable glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. I will retire my ſelfe wholy therfore from the world; I wil Cloyſter vp
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:183926:136"/> my ſenſes from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and vanities there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; they ſhall no longer frequent the meeting pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of profaner mindes; My hart ſhall bee a Cell, wherein my Thoughtes being throughly weaned from the deſire of all tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory pleaſures, ſhal ſing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually with a ſincere and mortified affection, <hi>Halleluiah, Halleluiah</hi> to the King of Kinges.<note place="margin">Luke 19.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi> could not poſſibly ſee Chriſt Ieſus in the crowd, but when he had him in his Houſe alone, his eyes were ſatisfyed with the view of that ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:183926:137"/> obiect. The ſhort-liued recreation that Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity brings with it, ſhal not lodge within the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of my boſome, I knowe that the laughter of a mad man, is a griefe to his friendes; and the mirth of a Sinner dooth make an Angell mourn; I will from hence-foorth therefore furniſh my ſelfe with a religious &amp; godly ſorrow, and being ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, I will run and ſeek for my bleſſed Sauiour. His Mother founde him not till ſhee had greeued exceedingly; nor <hi>Marie Magdalene,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 2.48.</note> till ſhee had
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:183926:137"/> wept exceſſiuely; they both lamented &amp; mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned bitterly,<note place="margin">Iohn 20.11</note> as <hi>for the loſse of an onely Sonne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 6.26.</note> or they could neuer elſe haue heard of him. I will not hope for better hap, but encourage my ſelfe by their example.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>LV.</head>
               <p>THe blewneſſe of the wound ſerueth to purge the euill,<note place="margin">Pro. 20, 30</note> and the ſtripes within the bowels of the belly. For it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the after-wiſdome, and <hi>Epimethean had I wiſt</hi> of mortall men, neuer to looke vp vnto Heauen for help, but in the midſt
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:183926:138"/> of their affliction. And then, <hi>Come</hi> ſay they, <hi>let vs returne to the Lord, for he hath ſpoyled vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and hee wil heale vs; he hath woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs, and he will bind vs vp.</hi> In their proſperitie they growe forgetfull of him that made them, and neuer thinke vppon the Croſſe of Chriſt, til they be croſt themſelues. Till <hi>Paule</hi> was ſtrooke with blidneſſe, he neuer asked Ieſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> what was to be done; nor did the Prodigall acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his fault, til hunger forced him to returne. <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> remembred not<note place="margin">2 Cron. 33.12.</note>
                  <pb n="247" facs="tcp:183926:138"/> to pray vnto the Lord, til he was in tribulation, &amp; then he humbled himſelf greatly before the GOD of his fathers. The carnal man will quickly ryot in his groth; if he bee not, either by infirmities, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, neceſſities, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or anguiſh ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and kept downe. <hi>When I am weak</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>then am I ſtrong.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12, 10.</note> And hereupon the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophet deſiring the conuerſion of ſinfulmen, <hi>Fill their faces, O Lorde,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with ſhume,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 83.16.</note> 
                  <hi>that they may ſeeke thy Name;</hi> and in another place. <hi>Let
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:183926:139"/> thy chasticementes and thy corrections bee multiplyed vppon them, and they will haſten to thee out of hand.</hi> They may be likened to a ſeruant that obeyeth not his Maiſter, but when his Sword is drawne; or vnto Swine, that till the comming of the ſtorme, will not leaue their wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in the mire. Nay ſome of them there are, ſo deſperately enamou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with that painted <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabell</hi> (Iniquity) that no indifferent meanes can weane them from her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5, 5.</note> they muſt of neceſſity be deliuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:183926:139"/> Sathan, for the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the fleſh, or their Spirit will bee hardly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the day of the lord; And ſuch were <hi>Hymenaeus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.20</note> whome <hi>Paule</hi> ſurrendred vp vnto him, that they might learne not to blaſpheme. A thing exceeding ſtrange, and like to <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> Riddle;<note place="margin">Iudg. 14.14</note> That out of the deuourer ſhold come meat, and ſweetneſſe out of the ſtrong; yet ſo it is. <hi>Vice</hi> ſheweth it ſelf vnder his Roofe, euen in the height of her beſtiality; the nakedneſſe thereof is quite diſcouered: no part
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:183926:140"/> of hir deformity but here is ſtalled out to the full ſhowe, and thrice thrice, wretched is that man, whome this cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſt. With al ſubmiſſion therefore, both of heart and minde, will I drinke the Cup which my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father ſhal put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hand; the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof ſhal not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright mee; 'tis for the ſtrengthening and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering of my crazy ſoul, and I will not grudge to take it. I will repaire vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde for helpe while my hurt is green, if once it putrify, there is
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:183926:140"/> no vſe of <hi>Linitiues;</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſsibly be cured but by <hi>Cautere</hi> or <hi>Inciſion.</hi> I will obey the ſummons of his glorious miniſters, and not ſtay til I be called by him: His voice is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible as thunder; it brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Caedars, and maketh <hi>Lebanon</hi> and <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion</hi> leape like the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Vnicornes;<note place="margin">Pſal. 29.6.</note> it diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the flames of Fire, and maketh the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Kadeſh</hi> to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: at the ſound there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the Hindes doe Calue, and the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts are diſcouered. Let <hi>Moſes</hi> therefore talk with<note place="margin">Exo. 20.19.</note>
                  <pb n="252" facs="tcp:183926:141"/> me, and I will heare him; but let not God talk with me, leaſt I dye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>LVI.</head>
               <p>SLoath is an enemy to Chriſtian Venues, &amp; he that ſerueth vnder the Lord of hoaſtes, muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to auoide it. His Souldiers muſt be ſtill in action, and vppon their march. To make a ſtande in the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is as diſtaſtfull to the King of heauen, as to retyre. The man of God that came vp from <hi>Iudah,</hi> to propheſie to <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the deſtruction of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,<note place="margin">King 13.24</note>
                  <pb n="253" facs="tcp:183926:141"/> though ſeduced by the Spirit of <hi>Vntruth,</hi> did pay the ſame forfeiture for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lingering, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch the Wife of <hi>Lot</hi> did for her looking b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cke. And it is auouched by the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of heauen, That he which is ſloathfull in his worke,<note place="margin">Prou. 18, 9.</note> is euen the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of him that is a great waſter. I will awaken therefore my ſlugg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh thoughtes, and with the preceptes of my bleſſed Sauiour, will I quicken their dull motion. Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding waters doe quic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lie putrifie, and without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, the healthieſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:183926:142"/> waxeth faint &amp; feeble. The Canker doth conſume the Braſſe, and ruſt the Iron, if they bee not vſed; yea, the luſtre of the pureſt Golde aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth by beeing long im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned in the Coffers of the Couetous. The Lorde therefore ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large my heart,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.32</note> and I wil run the way of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes. In vaine hath hee receiued the grace of God, that doth not ſhowe ſome ſigne of his proficiency. I wil imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate thoſe Kine, that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Arke from <hi>Ekro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 6.12</note> who lowed as they went,
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:183926:142"/> &amp; alwaies kept one path, not turning till they cam vnto <hi>Bethſhemeſh,</hi> eyther to the right hand or the left; I haue already char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my ſhoulders with the yoake of my Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and am entred into the ſtraight and ready way; no worldly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration or reſpect ſhall make me ſlacke my pace; I will onwards ſtill, and not ceaſe to ſigh vnder the burthen of it for my ſinnes, till I come vnto the glorious habitation of my bleſſed Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus, the Son of euerlaſting righteouſnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="256" facs="tcp:183926:143"/>
               <head>LVII.</head>
               <p>GOD is the Well-ſpring of true knowledge &amp; eternall wiſedome, from whence thoſe Fountaines of liuing Waters flowe, which who ſo taſteth of, ſhall neuer thirſt. It is hee that ſearcheth the heart and reines; it is he, that declareth vnto man what is his thought. Hee knoweth all things intuitiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and nothing can bee hid from his diſcerning Eye. But yet ſuch is the loue hee bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs, that willingly &amp; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly hee ſuffereth himſelfe to bee deceiued by vs. Hee proffereth vs the Kingdome
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:183926:143"/> of Heauen at a low rate, as if he knew not iuſtly the worth therof. The Apoſtles bought it of him for a leaking Fiſh-Boate, and ſome few broken Nets to boote: <hi>Zacheus</hi> had it for halfe his goodes: the Widdow for her mite: and ſome (O happineſſe beyond all hap!) for a Cup of colde Water onely: Nay the good will alone, and ſincere affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many towardes it, hath beene accepted, and thought ſufficient for the purchaſe. Whatſoeuer we haue of him is vndervalued; but he hath nothing from vs, which is not ouer-bought. Our earthly bodies coſt him the ſhedding of his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious blood; our cankered ſoules the laying downe of
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:183926:144"/> his immaculate and ſpotleſſe life; and what alas! is there in vs (poore ſinfull wretches that we are) which may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue ſuch an ineſtimable price.<note place="margin">Mat. 19.29.</note> Hee giueth vs a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth folde more then hee taketh, and ſuffereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee beguild euen with vnequall ſhares. For many times wee giue our youth to Sathan, and our age to him, who notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hee ſhould haue both doth take it quietly, and like a gentle Creditor is content with any thing from a bad Debter. But this conniuence, &amp; kinde forbearance of his, ſhall not embolden me in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny careleſſe courſe. All that I haue will I giue vnto him, yet thinke that al too little for ſo
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:183926:144"/> great and glorious an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance. Whatſoeuer I pay, nothing can equall it in eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. The whole world, in compariſon hereof,<note place="margin">Luke 15, 8.</note> is not to be valued, no not at the loſt groate. I will conſider how dearly my redeemer bought me, and endeauor to render vp my ſelfe in that regard, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hands, as pure and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect both in mind and body as I can: I wil conſecrate my ſelfe vnto the Lorde in the ſtrength and vigour of my yeares, and in my flouriſhing and able daies will I deuote my ſelfe to the ſeruice, and inuocation of his moſt holy name. Hee that diuideth ill, though he offer well, cannot but offend.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="234" facs="tcp:183926:145"/>
               <head>LVIII.</head>
               <p>THe waies of the Lorde are in the Whirle-wind and the ſtorme; the cloudes are the duſt of his feete. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan</hi> and <hi>Carmel</hi> waſt at his rebuke, and the floure of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon</hi> doth wither. The Mountaines retire from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, &amp; the hils do me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. His Maieſtie is great, his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer wonderfull; yet many wayes there are, and many meanes to vanquiſh &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due him. At the ſight of our dejection.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>His heart is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within him, and his reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:183926:145"/> are rouled together.</hi> He muſt of force reuerſe his iudgements, and ſtay to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the fierceneſſe of his intended wrath. But when with a zealous and feruent ſpirit we doe encounter him in prayer, then doe we bind him (as it were) hand and foote, that hee cannot ſtirre. <hi>Let mee alone</hi> (ſaide hee to <hi>Moſes) and giue my fury leaue to wax hot againſt this people.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo. 32, 10.</note> But the Prophet continued his charitable interceſſion, and would not ſuffer him to goe, till he had changed his minde.<note place="margin">Eſay 38, 1.</note> Hee had determined the death of <hi>Hezikiah,</hi> &amp; by the mouth of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> willed him to put his houſe in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for hee ſhould not liue, but the King hauing notice
<pb facs="tcp:183926:146"/>
                  <pb n="234" facs="tcp:183926:147"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="239" facs="tcp:183926:147"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="262" facs="tcp:183926:148"/> of this firme arreſt, turned his face vnto the wall, &amp; by the vertue of his prayers and teares preuaild ſo farre, that in the end,<note place="margin">Mat. 15, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ixit &amp; vicit,</hi> he both liued and ouercame. By this the woman of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> did ſurmount that ſetled hardneſſe, whereof our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour did make ſhewe vnto her.<note place="margin">Gen. 32, 28</note> In a worde, this is that wreſtling of the <hi>Patriarch,</hi> in which hee behaued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo valiantly, that he bore away the glorious title, and renowned name of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> in token of his victorious &amp; triumphall Conqueſt. But this doth maiſter but his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon onely. The Saints and Martyrs by their paines and ſufferances, doe breake into his territories, &amp; make their
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:183926:148"/> ſtation euen within his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines. Himſelfe beholdeth it, and cryeth out,<note place="margin">Mat. 11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen ſuffereth vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; and the violent take it away by force.</hi> I will humble my ſelfe therefore before the Lord my God, and vnto him will I ingenuouſly confeſſe, how ſinne and Sathan haue vtterly ſpoyled me of all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall graces and endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and that my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence onely hath eſcapt their fury, to bring me tydings of the loſſe. With my miſery will I excite his mercy, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake his compasſion with the vehemency of my owne pasſions. I will faſten on him by deuout and earneſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, and not let him goe, except hee bleſſe mee.
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:183926:149"/> With patience wil I arme my ſelfe againſt all hardneſſe &amp; ſlight, both Death and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to make my paſſage to the top of <hi>Sion,</hi> and through the ſtreetes of his impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Citty, the New <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:183926:149"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
